<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://benjaminguinet.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://benjaminguinet.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-05-15T08:30:18+00:00</updated><id>https://benjaminguinet.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Sexual selection, from sexy dancing to cheating, anything goes!</title><link href="https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2025/Pop-science-Sexual_selection/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sexual selection, from sexy dancing to cheating, anything goes!"/><published>2025-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2025/Pop-science-Sexual_selection</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2025/Pop-science-Sexual_selection/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction"><strong>Introduction</strong></h2> <p>Watching a wildlife documentary or simply taking a walk in the woods, you’re bound to have come across an animal with extravagant characteristics. So extravagant, in fact, that you might well wonder whether it doesn’t go against natural selection. Take, for example, a peacock’s bulky tail, the enormous fins of a fighting fish or a deer’s impressive antlers. They’re beautiful ornaments, yes, but they’re also very awkward to move around on and highly visible to predators! The question then arises: how can such features be selected when they seem to have a negative impact on the survival of the individuals that wear them?</p> <p>The answer lies in a concept that I’m about to introduce to you: sexual selection. In the rest of this article, we’ll look at why, in the vast majority of species, females choose males and how they choose them.</p> <p>We will then look at other non-human animals to understand some of the strategies that have been selected over the course of evolution to persuade females to mate. We’ll see that there are cheats in the animal world and that sometimes strength and beauty are no match for some clever little buggers!</p> <h2 id="sexual-selection-a-story-about-sex"><strong>Sexual selection, a story about sex</strong></h2> <p>What we remember from the concept of natural selection developed by Darwin and Wallace (more details in our article on this subject) is that individuals with the most adaptive characteristics survive better, reproduce better and are therefore selected from generation to generation. However, if you’re an observer of nature, you should be able to spot an inconsistency in all these stories… In fact, if you look closely at the animal world, you’ll see that males and females sometimes have different phenotypes. Males are often more colourful or have flashy ornaments. Females generally have more discreet attributes. In terms of the theory of natural selection, it seems counter-intuitive that individuals should be selected when they are sporting multicoloured coats that make them more visible to predators and make them look very cluttered.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2_BAS_ornements-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2_BAS_ornements-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2_BAS_ornements-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/2_BAS_ornements.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>But were Darwin and Wallace wrong? What’s the point of favouring such disabling characteristics that increase the probability of dying? Well, the answer can be summed up in one simple phrase: to gain access to reproduction!</p> <p>Both knew that natural selection could not be expected to favour the evolution of disadvantageous traits. Although they had differing ideas on the subject, they were nevertheless able to offer a solution to this problem: sexual selection. In his book ‘The descent of man and selection in relation to sex’[1] published in 1874, Darwin proposed a new evolutionary process different from natural selection. This process does not depend on a struggle for existence in relation to other organisms or environmental conditions, but on a struggle between individuals of one sex for possession of the other sex.</p> <h3 id="definition-of-sexual-selection-">Definition of sexual selection :</h3> <p><em>Sexual selection is a theory according to which the evolution of certain remarkable physical traits such as pronounced colouring, increased size or striking ornamentation in animals can make it easier for those who possess them to obtain mates.</em></p> <h2 id="an-explanation-for-the-war-of-the-sexes-anisogamy"><strong>An explanation for the war of the sexes: anisogamy</strong></h2> <p>But why is it that, in the majority of cases, it’s the males who end up with the extra ornaments!</p> <p>The most widespread theory to explain this phenomenon is anisogamy. ‘Anisos’ means non-equal and ‘gamos’ means marriage. Anisogamy therefore refers to a form of fertilisation in which the gametes of the two sexes differ, particularly in size.</p> <p>The male gametes (spermatozoa) are much smaller than the female gametes (oocytes). In humans, an oocyte measures around 120µm whereas a spermatozoon measures around 50µm. In addition, there is a significant difference in production cost between a male gamete and a female gamete. Oocytes live longer and contain nutritional resources, but are more ‘expensive’ (metabolically) to produce.</p> <p>The main idea behind this theory is that males produce more and cheaper gametes. Females have only a limited and precious supply. This imbalance will lead to sexual conflict. Females have an interest in carefully choosing a male, while males have an interest in fertilising as many females as possible.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/3_anisogamie-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/3_anisogamie-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/3_anisogamie-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/3_anisogamie.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Over the course of evolution, this war of the sexes has put males in competition with each other for access to a limited quantity of female gametes, and thus to the much-hoped-for paternity.</p> <p><strong>NB</strong> : it is interesting to ask how anisogamy emerged. But also why there are differentiated sexes. One of the answers lies in the fact that it prevents self-fertilisation. If you’re interested, read <a href="https://sfecologie.org/regard/r78-fev-2018-giraud-billiard-evolution-anisogamie/">this article</a> on the subject.</p> <h2 id="the-cornelian-choice-of-females-between-direct-and-indirect-benefits"><strong>The Cornelian choice of females, between direct and indirect benefits</strong></h2> <p>The males’ objectives are clear. They need females to ensure that they have offspring, and they are competing to get them. What do the females gain and why choose one criterion over another?</p> <p>In some cases it’s quite clear. If we take the example of a female gorilla given the choice between a pudgy gorilla with low social status or a dominant, muscular gorilla, it’s easy to see why she would choose the dominant gorilla. The male probably has access to more food and can protect his territory. The female gains physical security and food. Now, if we take the example of the peacock, it’s a little less intuitive to understand why females prefer the males who do the best cartwheels.</p> <p>The choice of females is based on two main categories of criteria: <strong>direct</strong> and <strong>indirect</strong> advantages.</p> <h2 id="sexual-selection---direct-advantages"><strong>Sexual selection - Direct advantages</strong></h2> <p>A direct advantage will be immediately identifiable by the female and will instantly increase her fertility or lifespan. For example, females can obtain: better access to food, protection from harassing males or help in raising their offspring, or avoid being infected by parasites (or other diseases) by choosing healthy males.</p> <p>Direct benefits can be of various kinds. Some species offer nuptial gifts, which are usually food. This behaviour is found in a wide variety of organisms such as birds, insects and spiders. Sometimes there is a positive correlation between the size of the gift and the copulation time allowed by the female. For example, if the male provides the female with a large prey item, he will be able to transfer more spermatozoa [3,4]. In other species, such as the Red-backed Black Widow, males offer themselves as a <strong>nuptial gift</strong> by allowing themselves to be eaten [5].</p> <p>Another direct and seemingly obvious advantage is choosing a sexual partner who will help raise the young for some species. Females will choose a good father to help them build a nest and feed the young. These behaviours are observed in many bird species, but also in mice.</p> <p>A final example can be found in bullfrogs. Females will prefer males with the ‘best’ territory. The eggs will thus be protected from predators during their development. Sexual selection - Indirect advantages</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/4_BAS_avantages-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/4_BAS_avantages-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/4_BAS_avantages-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/4_BAS_avantages.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="sexual-selection---indirect-advantages"><strong>Sexual selection - Indirect advantages</strong></h2> <p>An indirect advantage is less obvious to the female and can be interpreted as a gamble. The female will have to detect whether a male is a good partner on the basis of clues that are more or less clear (to our human eyes). If she wins her bet, the female will produce healthy offspring who will in turn be able to produce numerous offspring, indirectly increasing the female’s reproductive success.</p> <p>To make her choice, the female will rely on specific signals that will be interpreted as quality indicators. These are often exaggerated physical traits that have been selected in males over the course of evolution. These are called secondary sexual characteristics. There are two complementary theories to explain the appearance of these strange characteristics.</p> <h3 id="when-males-get-carried-away">When males get carried away…</h3> <p><strong>Fisher’s ‘runaway’ theory</strong> proposes that, over the generations, a non-adaptive trait that is visible and guarantees good quality will be selected by the females. A positive feedback loop then follows. Females are increasingly interested in this characteristic, so sexual selection will encourage it to increase.</p> <p>For example, females will choose the males with the longest plumage because their offspring will also inherit long plumage and will in turn be chosen by the females of the next generation, maximising the probability of gene dispersal (Fisher 1930).</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/5_BAS_fisher-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/5_BAS_fisher-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/5_BAS_fisher-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/5_BAS_fisher.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>This mechanism will then lead to unbridled selection for the exaggeration of ornament and preference. This mechanism will continue until the production costs of the ornament exceed the reproductive benefit of possessing it. In theory it could be any non-adaptive trait as long as females can easily compare them. The cost only appears at the final stage of an evolutionary spiral.</p> <h3 id="the-theory-of-handicap-and-good-genes">The theory of handicap and good genes</h3> <p>The alternative theory to Fisherian runaway evolution is called the handicap theory. It is also known as the good genes theory.</p> <p>According to this <strong>handicap theory</strong>, males with extravagant traits that are even dangerous for their survival would be males of good overall quality. Indeed, males disabled by an extravagant trait were able to survive in a hostile environment even though (for example) they had to drag around a huge multicoloured tail (Zahavi 1975). Their extravagant character would therefore be an honest signal about their physical condition and therefore their “good genes”.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/6_BAS_handicap-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/6_BAS_handicap-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/6_BAS_handicap-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/6_BAS_handicap.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>All these mechanisms are based on the supposed existence of genes conferring greater vigour (“good genes” hypothesis), revealed by external handicaps and therefore only able to be developed by individuals of very high individual quality. However, evidence that females select for good genes remains scarce despite decades of studies on mate choice in many organisms. This apparent lack of consensus continues to create debate about the importance of the good gene model in the field of evolutionary biology.</p> <h2 id="what-strategies-do-males-use"><strong>What strategies do males use?</strong></h2> <h3 id="pre-copulatory-behaviour">Pre-copulatory behaviour</h3> <p>Most of the time, when we think of sexual selection, we think of confrontations as the mating season approaches or sumptuous courtship displays. In the animal kingdom, these strategies are widespread and occur before copulation. If these behaviours have been selected over the course of evolution, it’s mainly because they allow the best males to be chosen. Both in terms of <strong>indirect advantage</strong> (if I choose the male who wins, then my offspring will probably also inherit the genes that will enable them to win the competition in turn), or <strong>direct advantage</strong> (if I choose the strongest male, then I increase my probability of survival and that of my offspring because I will be better protected from predators).</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/7_BAS_strategies-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/7_BAS_strategies-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/7_BAS_strategies-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/7_BAS_strategies.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="sperm-competition-sexual-selection-in-detail"><strong>Sperm competition, sexual selection in detail</strong></h2> <p>Females sometimes choose not to put all their eggs in one basket. In these species, they often mate with different males to maximise their chances of having healthy offspring. In this situation, the competition between males takes place at sperm level and is called sperm competition.</p> <p>Males have no interest in other males impregnating the female with whom they have just mated. Thus, in the course of evolution, multiple strategies have emerged at different times during the copulatory stage.</p> <h3 id="before-copulation-the-hunter-loses-his-place">Before copulation, the hunter loses his place</h3> <p>In some species (such as dragonflies), when the female has already been fertilised, the next male may take several hours to clean the female’s spermatic cavity before introducing his seed. In this way, using small feather dusters, he eliminates the sperm of any predecessors and increases his own chances of paternity.</p> <h3 id="during-copulation">During copulation</h3> <p>In order to prolong the copulation period, some males will not let go of the female an inch. The aim is to maximise the chances of their sperm being fertilised during mating. To achieve this, some males act as copulatory plugs. In some phasms, genital contact can last up to 79 days! [10].</p> <h3 id="after-copulation">After copulation</h3> <p><strong>Obstruction of the genital tract</strong>: Some species (cockroaches, locusts and other insects) will accompany their sperm with a substance (cement glands) designed to obstruct the female’s genital tract during subsequent mating (e.g. dung flies).</p> <p><strong>Induced contraception</strong>: Another strategy consists of releasing a substance that prevents subsequent mating. In mosquitoes, males produce a substance through their secondary sex gland that inhibits the receptivity of inseminated females. As a result, they refuse most matings with other males [11].</p> <p><strong>Guarding females</strong>: Others will simply keep their eyes on the females and keep away any males likely to want to impregnate the female [3], as in the case of certain monkeys or mallard ducks.</p> <p><strong>Ugly beauty</strong>: Another tactic is to make females unattractive to other males. This phenomenon is particularly well known in moths. Males deposit anti-aphrodisiacs on females during mating [3].</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/8_competition_spermatique-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/8_competition_spermatique-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/8_competition_spermatique-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/8_competition_spermatique.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="the-animal-world-is-full-of-cheats"><strong>The animal world is full of cheats!</strong></h2> <p>So far we’ve seen that secondary sexual characteristics (for example, the peacock’s tail) were honest indicators of the underlying quality of the males. The costs associated with producing and maintaining these extravagant features informed the females about the overall health of the males that wore them. The more physically fit a male is, the more access he has to quality energy resources. And the more he is able to waste them strutting around the forest with a very long tail. Some males have seen this as an opportunity to optimise their energy allocation by reducing certain costs associated with secondary sexual traits without damaging their overall reproductive success. This is where cheating comes in!</p> <h3 id="examples-of-cheaters">Examples of cheaters</h3> <p>Some male spiders fill their nuptial gifts with silk instead of prey to fool females and reproduce for longer [14].</p> <p>As they are unable to compete with the larger males, some will trick the females into fertilisation all the same. In some amphibians, the smaller males will closely follow the larger males and grab the females attracted to them.</p> <p>The males of other fish species will take advantage of fertilisation by throwing sperm into the water to mix theirs with that of other fish. In some beetles, the males will fertilise the females in secret while a larger male stands guard.</p> <p>Finally, many females choose males who will give up all their time to help with feeding or defend the territory. The males thus find themselves torn between staying with the female and impregnating as many females as possible. As a result, it is not uncommon to observe males sneaking off to impregnate other females. A study of birds, the Prothonotary Warbler, showed that nearly 27% of offspring were identified as the result of extra-pair mating [15]!</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/9_BAS_tricheries-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/9_BAS_tricheries-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/9_BAS_tricheries-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/9_BAS_tricheries.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="a-final-word"><strong>A final word</strong></h2> <p>Historically, the field of sexual selection is still very young. Indeed, research in this field only began in the 1960s [22]. So it’s not surprising that the concept of sexual selection remains little known, even though the general public is already familiar with natural selection.</p> <p>Science is not neutral. Scientists are caught up in an axiological matrix from which they cannot free themselves, and from which it is undesirable for them to free themselves, as this would deprive science of its human dimension. It is wrong to think that when a scientist puts down his hat and coat and puts on his white coat, he removes the interpretative filter between us and reality.</p> <p>So we need to remain cautious about the observations we make about the world around us. Although we can have very serious studies on the subject, the fact remains that our perception of things is subjective, especially in a world as complex as ours. The idea of a common value is difficult to maintain. So now, more than ever, we need to share the knowledge and viewpoints of a diversity of researchers on a research topic, because that’s how we can minimise our personal interpretations.</p> <h2 id="back-to-the-article"><strong>Back to the article</strong></h2> <p>In this article we have just seen a few examples that I have chosen, but in reality there are as many differences as there are species. I haven’t even mentioned species that don’t reproduce sexually or those in which the sex changes over the course of an individual’s life (but that’s only part of the story)! Personally, I’m still fascinated by all the singularities that surround us, especially as sexuality in general shapes and occupies a key place in evolutionary processes: the passing on of genes!</p> <p><strong>References</strong></p> <p>1- Darwin, C., 1875. The Descent of Man, and Selection in relation to Sex. Nature, 11(277)</p> <p>2- T, A., 2021. R78 : Pourquoi des sexes différents, et pourquoi deux le plus souvent? par T. Giraud et S. Billiard - sfecologie.org.</p> <p>3- Albo, M. and Peretti, A., 2015. Worthless and Nutritive Nuptial Gifts: Mating Duration, Sperm Stored and Potential Female Decisions in Spiders. PLOS ONE, 10(6)</p> <p>4- Gwynne, D., 2008. Sexual Conflict over Nuptial Gifts in Insects. Annual Review of Entomology, 53(1)</p> <p>5- Andrade, M., 1998. Female hunger can explain variation in cannibalistic behavior despite male sacrifice in redback spiders. Behavioral Ecology, 9(1)</p> <p>6- Toft, S. and Albo, M., 2016. The shield effect: nuptial gifts protect males against pre-copulatory sexual cannibalism. Biology Letters, 12(5)</p> <p>7- Cecie Starr and Ralph Taggart, Biology – the Unity and Diversity of Life, 6th Ed., Wadsworth Publishing Company, 1992</p> <p>8- Edward T. Hall, The Hidden Dimension, New York, Anchor Books, 1966</p> <p>9- Córdoba-Aguilar, A., Uhía, E. and Rivera, A., 2003. Sperm competition in Odonata (Insecta): the evolution of female sperm storage and rivals’ sperm displacement. Journal of Zoology, 261(4)</p> <p>10- Gangrade, G., 1964. Accessory glands of female phasmid, Necroscia sparaxes Westwood. Annals and Magazine of Natural History, 7(84)</p> <p>11- Helinski, M., et al., 2012. Duration and dose-dependency of female sexual receptivity responses to seminal fluid proteins in Aedes albopictus and Ae. aegypti mosquitoes. Journal of Insect Physiology, 58(10)</p> <p>12- Parker, G., 1970. Sperm competition and its evolutionary consequences in the insects. Biological Reviews, 45(4)</p> <p>13- van Noordwijk, A. and de Jong, G., 1986. Acquisition and Allocation of Resources: Their Influence on Variation in Life History Tactics. The American Naturalist, 128(1)</p> <p>14 - Ghislandi, P., et al., 2017. Silk wrapping of nuptial gifts aids cheating behaviour in male spiders. Behavioral Ecology, 28(3)</p> <p>15 – Morton Catherine Heidrich Virginia., 2013. PhD thesis. Who’s Your Daddy? A Study of Extra-Pair Copulation and Mating Behaviors of Protonotaria citrea Behaviors of Protonotaria citrea.</p> <p>16 - Sinervo, B. and Lively, C., 1996. The rock–paper–scissors game and the evolution of alternative male strategies. Nature, 380(6571)</p> <p>17- Puts, D., 2021. Human sexual selection. 20015. Current Opinion in Psychology.</p> <p>18- Scott, I., et al., 2014. Human preferences for sexually dimorphic faces may be evolutionarily novel. PNAS, 111(40)</p> <p>19- Wheatley, J.,et al., 2014. Women’s faces and voices are cues to reproductive potential in industrial and forager societies. Evolution and Human Behavior, 35(4)</p> <p>20- Collins, S. and Missing, C., 2003. Vocal and visual attractiveness are related in women. Animal Behaviour, 65(5)</p> <p>21- Singh, D., et al., 2010. Cross-cultural consensus for waist–hip ratio and women’s attractiveness. Evolution and Human Behavior, 31(3)</p> <p>22- Giraldeau, L., Cézilly, F. and Danchin, E., 2005. Écologie comportementale. Paris: Dunod.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="pop-science"/><category term="Sexual"/><category term="selection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Popular scientific paper]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tales lull our childhood and trace our history</title><link href="https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2025/Pop-science-Tales-tel-our-history/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tales lull our childhood and trace our history"/><published>2025-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2025/Pop-science-Tales-tel-our-history</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2025/Pop-science-Tales-tel-our-history/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction"><strong>Introduction</strong></h2> <p>We’ve all read or listened to fabulous stories from a book of fairy tales. These stories make us dream, have nightmares, laugh or think. But where do they come from? To answer this question, I propose to analyse the history of these stories. We will see that stories are a profound part of ourselves and of the history we all share.</p> <p>Firstly, we will look at the reasons that have led and continue to lead human beings to invent stories. We will discover that every culture has its own stories, and that these stories evolve over the centuries.</p> <p>We will then look at how science, and in particular phylogeny (which we will define, don’t worry!), can be used to establish links between the evolution of species and that of stories.</p> <p>Finally, we will explore the meandering imaginations of our ancestors by analysing 2 stories with singular origins:</p> <p><strong>Little Red Riding Hood</strong> <strong>The Cosmic Hunt in the Berber Sky</strong></p> <p>Now it’s time to embark on this superb journey together!</p> <h2 id="why-do-humans-tell-stories"><strong>Why do humans tell stories?</strong></h2> <p>Humans have been telling stories for a very long time, even before they could put them down on paper. Stories, like languages, are in essence information that has been passed down from one person to another over the millennia. To tell a story is to share an experience, an idea or moral values which, when passed on, shape and colour our understanding of our past and present. But have these stories evolved over the centuries?</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Contes-evolution-pangolin-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Contes-evolution-pangolin-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Contes-evolution-pangolin-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Contes-evolution-pangolin.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3 id="have-these-stories-evolved-over-the-centuries"><strong>Have these stories evolved over the centuries?</strong></h3> <p>Versions of a story often reflect specific moral standards and mores close to the social classes that tell them. So it’s not unusual to see adaptations that meet the needs of their audience [1].</p> <p>[FIGURE2]</p> <p>Modern stories, though imprinted in the memories of countless storytellers, have been completely transformed from their original versions. Over time, these stories have been imbued with the various desires, struggles and complaints of their tellers, and provide perfect snapshots of the societies that created or modified them.</p> <p>Let’s take a very famous example. Jean de la Fontaine wrote a fable called ‘The Court of the Lion’, which is a story inspired by another fable called ‘The Reigning King’ written by Phaedra. Jean de la Fontaine modified the story to make it rhyme and, above all, to reflect the reality of Louis XIV’s court.</p> <h3 id="is-storytelling-universal"><strong>Is storytelling universal?</strong></h3> <p>Across the centuries and across borders, we always find stories associated with particular eras or cultures [2]. Stories from the Bible such as Noah’s Ark, Greek myths such as Narcissus or even much more recent legends such as Slenderman, which emerged on the internet in the early 2000s, come to mind. Some stories are also known to have originated in particular cultures. Examples include Peter and the Wolf in Russian culture, Hensel and Gretel in German culture, Little Thumb in French culture and Ali Baba and the Forty Thieves in Persian/Arabic culture.</p> <p>The disturbing thing is that when you leaf through all these stories in the famous book by the Grimm brothers [3], you realise that some of them bear disturbing similarities. This is the case with the story of <strong>Little Red Riding Hood</strong>, for example, which can be found (in different versions) in many cultures (bear with us, we’ll be analysing this famous example together a little later)!</p> <h2 id="using-biology-to-solve-folklore-problems"><strong>Using biology to solve folklore problems</strong></h2> <h3 id="a-question-then-arises-in-folkloristics-the-study-of-popular-traditions-and-customs-where-do-these-stories-come-from"><strong>A question then arises in folkloristics (the study of popular traditions and customs): where do these stories come from?</strong></h3> <p>To answer this question, we need to have access to traces of these stories that have survived the centuries. However, most of these stories are passed down through oral tradition. There are few historical traces of these texts (just as there are for the study of fossils). Studying the history of these stories can therefore prove very complicated, even using conventional tools of literary analysis. To overcome these difficulties, a promising scientific approach to folkloristics has emerged. The aim is to apply mathematical tools used by biologists to decipher the evolution of living species [4-6].</p> <h3 id="but-how-does-it-work"><strong>But how does it work?</strong></h3> <p>To better understand how these mathematical tools work, let’s draw an analogy with the evolution of species and the way scientists record their evolutionary history.</p> <p>Evolution, as a theory explaining the diversity of living nature, was developed by biologists such as Charles Darwin and Alfred Russel Wallace in the middle of the 19th century [7]. In a nutshell (see our article on the subject), the theory of evolution explains how organisms change over time. This transformation takes place as a result of genetic changes. These changes can have an impact on the physical or behavioural characteristics of individuals. If these changes bring them one or more advantages, they will be passed on more easily to their descendants. This theory, and all the contributions that have followed, have enabled us to take a fresh look at the processes of life.</p> <p>Thanks to this principle, it is possible to study the evolution of living beings and determine their family relationships. This is known as ‘phylogeny’.</p> <p>Ouch, that’s off to a good start, already a barbaric name for a scientist! Well, not so much if we look at its etymology. Phylogeny comes from the Greek phylon, meaning tribe or species, and gennan, meaning origin or formation. The result is a word that refers to <strong>the study of the formation of species</strong>. Phylogeny studies the formation and evolution of living organisms, as well as the relationships between these organisms.</p> <p>[FIGURE3]</p> <h3 id="the-link-between-phylogeny-and-fairytales"><strong>The link between phylogeny and fairytales</strong></h3> <p>You may be wondering what the link is between phylogeny and my stories? Well, as the famous anthropologist Claude Lévi-Strauss [8] pointed out, stories, like organisms, probably evolve through progressive changes in hereditary traits! Just like species, the original forms of stories mutate, evolve and spread as they spread. They adapt to different environments and accumulate modifications that are passed down through the generations. They can thus give rise to locally distinct tales.</p> <p>To examine how stories vary between cultures and periods, it is possible to define a series of characteristics, called myths, and compare them between story variants.</p> <p>These characteristics might include the gender of the hero (girl or boy), the species of animal that embodies the villain (wolf, tiger or ogre) or the location of the story (forest, town, mountain).</p> <p>[FIGURE4]</p> <p>The idea is to analyse these characteristics as if they were physical characteristics or genes and to use them to reconstruct the genealogy of the story, just as we would for a species phylogeny. So, if two histories have similar characteristics, it is likely that they have a recent common origin.</p> <h2 id="little-red-riding-hood"><strong>Little Red Riding Hood</strong></h2> <p>Little Red Riding Hood is one of the world’s most popular tales. This tale delicately explores our greatest fears. It’s a story about the struggle between good and evil, about greed and hope, about responsibility and second chances.</p> <h3 id="the-classic-tale"><strong>The classic tale</strong></h3> <p>[FIGURE4]</p> <p>If this story rings a bell, it’s because you’ve inherited the first French version of Little Red Riding Hood. It was written by Charles Perrault in the late 17th century [9,10], and later collected by the Grimm brothers [3].</p> <p>If you’re frowning and thinking that this isn’t the version you know, well, that’s only to be expected, as there are many other versions around the world! In some versions, there is no hunter and the little girl manages to escape on the pretext of a pressing desire; in others, the heroine’s characteristic red colour doesn’t even appear.</p> <h3 id="strangely-similar-tales"><strong>Strangely similar tales</strong></h3> <p>[FIGURE5]</p> <p>Strange similarities with Little Red Riding Hood, don’t you think?</p> <p>What’s even more disturbing is that there are many other stories around the world that bear a striking resemblance to these 2 tales, in Africa and East Asia for example [10-11].</p> <p>This raises an interesting question: don’t all these tales have the same origin?</p> <p>And what if I were to tell you that to answer this question we can use the contributions of biology seen above? Surprising, isn’t it? Little Red Riding Hood: an old story</p> <p>Long before the scientific study that follows, anthropologists were already interested in the tales of Little Red Riding Hood and The Wolf and the 7 kids because of their strange similarities. They did not know whether the two tales had common or distinct origins.</p> <p>[FIGURE6]</p> <p>To unravel these questions, one researcher carried out a phylogenetic study. He had to look at all the stories associated with Little Red Riding Hood: 58 versions and no fewer than 72 plot variants [12]! And to answer the question of their origin, there’s only one solution: read them all! As you can probably imagine, it’s very complicated to collect all this data. This often leads (as in this case) to choices that are more or less debatable [13]. Nonetheless, this study has opened up the field to other explorers of folklore, enabling them to carry out more rigorous work in the future.</p> <h3 id="geographical-origins"><strong>Geographical origins</strong></h3> <p>Finally, the results show that ‘Little Red Riding Hood’ and ‘The Wolf and the 7 kids’ originated in Europe. Traces of Little Red Riding Hood can be found as far back as the Middle Ages [14]. Nevertheless, there are enough differences between them to be considered as 2 tales with very different origins.</p> <p>The variants found in Africa are more likely to be modified versions of ‘The Wolf and the 7 Kids’. The hypothesis is that this tale was introduced to African populations through trade or colonialism. It was then modified to create a new version that spread to societies in the centre and south of the continent, even reaching as far as the Caribbean islands. As for the tales told in Asia entitled ‘The Tiger and the Grandmother’, although it would appear to be a “hybrid” tale that evolved by mixing elements of ‘Little Red Riding Hood’ and ‘The Wolf and the 7 Kids’, the mystery remains.</p> <p>Interesting, isn’t it?</p> <p>To convince you (just a little more) of the value of studying the origins of fairy tales using phylogenetic analysis, here’s a second example that’s just as fascinating.</p> <h2 id="cosmic-hunting-in-the-berber-sky"><strong>Cosmic hunting in the Berber sky</strong></h2> <h3 id="15000-years-ago"><strong>15,000 years ago…</strong></h3> <p>Let’s continue with a much older story.</p> <p>[FIGURE7]</p> <p>In the Palaeolithic period, when our ancestors were still hunter-gatherers, none of this existed. The cap was not invented until the early 19th century, the crown in Antiquity, and what we might think of as a saucepan is not much older. Humans of that era had a completely different way of looking at life, much more in touch with nature. But how do we know what they were imagining?</p> <p>What if I told you that once again, thanks to phylogenetic methods, it was possible to try and infer the imaginations of our ancestors? You might be sceptical, and you would be right, but the approach is nonetheless worthy of our attention. The myth</p> <p>It all starts with a story that is widespread among the peoples of Africa, Europe, Asia and America [15]: the Cosmic Hunt. Although the animals and constellations may differ, all versions of the Cosmic Hunt share a common thread. A man chases or kills one or more animals, and the creatures are transformed into constellations.</p> <p>[FIGURE8]</p> <p>Other versions are found all over the world, such as that of the Iroquois peoples of North America. In this one, three hunters pursue a bear, the blood of the wounded animal staining the leaves of the autumn forest. The bear climbs a mountain and leaps into the sky. The hunters and the bear become the constellation of the Big Dipper. For the Chukchi, a Siberian people, the constellation Orion is a hunter chasing a reindeer, Cassiopeia.</p> <p>How can we explain these strange similarities that can be found in different places? One possibility is to consider a convergence hypothesis (i.e. an appearance independent of history in distant regions). Many cultures around the world would have produced similar myths because of a sort of unified subconscious? As if a collective psyche had driven us to explain the world using the same symbols. But this does not seem to be the most likely hypothesis, given the work of a French researcher.</p> <p>[FIGURE9]</p> <h2 id="the-phylogenetic-study"><strong>The phylogenetic study</strong></h2> <p>In this study, 47 versions of the story and 93 variants were studied [15]! The researcher noted that these versions are very rarely found in Australia. And practically never found in Indonesia or New Guinea. On the other hand, numerous versions are found on both sides of the Bering Strait (the arm of the sea that separates Eastern Siberia from Alaska). This strait was above sea level around 20,000 years ago [16,17]. These various elements, combined with phylogenetic reconstructions, would therefore seem to suggest that this story has a very ancient origin that goes back to the common roots of the Berbers and the European hunter-gatherers.</p> <p>Human migration data also seems to corroborate this reconstruction of the myth. Our ancestors migrating to the Americas from the Eurasian continent would have taken this story with them (on several occasions) before the Bering Strait was buried under the waters of the Pacific. The presence of this story in Africa also seems to support an already known hypothesis according to which humans returned to the African continent from Eurasia.</p> <p>This researcher has even attempted to reconstruct the original story straight from the imagination of humans who lived more than 15,000 years ago. Here it is: “A large herbivore, probably an elk, was chased by a hunter. To escape, the elk galloped up into the sky, where it was transformed by a burst of light into a cluster of stars to form the constellation we now call the Big Dipper”. Of course, this is only an approximation. Nevertheless, it is an interesting attempt at reconstruction that has the merit of nourishing our imagination.</p> <h2 id="conclusion-between-tales-and-stories"><strong>Conclusion, between tales and stories</strong></h2> <p>It is quite remarkable that these stories have survived without being written down. They were told long before our modern languages existed, in dialects that have now disappeared. And yet these stories have endured thanks to the power of storytelling since time immemorial. The motifs in the tales are timeless and universal, involving dichotomies such as good and evil, love and hate, moral and immoral… In the end, although they are often regarded as fictional, and even as a form of narrative for children, folk tales nourish and will continue to nourish our collective imagination.</p> <h2 id="final-word"><strong>Final word</strong></h2> <p>Throughout the ages, the ways in which stories are told have changed. At the dawn of humanity, our ancestors probably told their stories from a natural fantasy around a fire. Today, this can be done at the click of a mouse. We are lucky enough to have access to all these stories! So we should make the most of them. But we should also continue to share them and draw inspiration from them to invent new stories, because if there’s one thing humanity can be proud of, it’s its overflowing imagination.</p> <p><strong>Author:</strong> Benjamin Guinet <strong>Illustrations:</strong> Vincent Lhuillier</p> <h2 id="references"><strong>References</strong></h2> <ol> <li> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>Encyclopedia.com., 2020. Evolution Of Fairy Tales</td> <td>Encyclopedia.Com.</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> </li> <li>Hughes, H., 1998. Storytelling Encyclopedia:98252David Adams Leeming, Marion Sader Edited by. Storytelling Encyclopedia: Historical, Cultural, and Multiethnic Approaches to Oral Traditions Around the World. Phoenix, Az. and London</li> <li>Grimm J, Grimm W., 1812. Children’s and Household Tales. Gottingen.</li> <li>Julien d’Huy et Jean-Loïc Le Quellec., 2004. « Comment reconstruire la préhistoire des mythes ? Applications d’outils phylogénétiques à une tradition orale »</li> <li>Korotayev, D, Khaltourina., 2011. Myths and Genes: a Deep Historical Reconstruction. Moscow: Librokom/URSS (ISBN 978–5–397–01175–4)</li> <li>Thuillard, M., Le Quellec, J., d’Huy, J. and Berezkin, Y., 2018. A Large-Scale Dtudy of World. Trames. Journal of the Humanities and Social Sciences, 22(4), p.407.</li> <li>Darwin, C. R. &amp; A. R. Wallace., 1858. Proceedings of the meeting of the Linnean Society held on July 1st, 1858. Journal of the Proceedings of the Linnean Society. Zoology 3: liv-lvi.</li> <li>Lévi-Strauss Claude., 1971. Mythologique4. L’Homme nu. Paris, Plon, 681p.</li> <li>Perrault C.,1697. Histoires ou Contes du temps passe´. Hood’’. Speculum 67: 549–575</li> <li>Frazer JG., 1889. A South African Red Riding-Hood. The Folk-Lore Journal 7:</li> <li>Ikeda H., 1971. A Type and Motif Index of Japanese Folk Literature. Helsinki: FF Communications</li> <li>Jamshid J. Tehrani., 2013. The Phylogeny of Little Red Riding Hood, PLOS ONE, vol. 8, n°11: e78871.</li> <li>Patrice Lajoye, Julien d’Huy and Jean-Loïc Le Quellec., 2013. reply to tethrani ; http://nouvellemythologiecomparee.hautetfort.com</li> <li>Ziolkowski JM., 1992. A fairy tale from before fairy tales: Egbert of Liege’s ‘‘De puella a lupellis seruata’’ and the medieval background of ‘‘Little Red Riding</li> <li>Da Silva, S. and Tehrani, J., 2016. Comparative phylogenetic analyses uncover the ancient roots of Indo-European folktales. Royal Society Open Science, 3(1), p.150645.</li> <li>Bond, J.D., 2019. Paleodrainage map of Beringia. Yukon Geological Survey,</li> <li>Geggel, L., 2019. Humans Crossed The Bering Land Bridge To People The Americas. Here’S What It Looked Like 18,000 Years Ago.. [online] livescience.com.</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="pop-science"/><category term="Tales"/><category term="trace"/><category term="our"/><category term="history"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Popular scientific paper]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra</title><link href="https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra"/><published>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/"><![CDATA[<p>May 14, 2024[[read-time]] min read We’re introducing a series of updates across the Gemini family of models, including the new 1.5 Flash, our lightweight model for speed and efficiency, and Project Astra, our vision for the future of AI assistants. In December, we launched our first natively multimodal model Gemini 1.0 in three sizes: Ultra, Pro and Nano. Just a few months later we released 1.5 Pro, with enhanced performance and a breakthrough long context window of 1 million tokens.Developers and enterprise customers have been putting 1.5 Pro to use in incredible ways and finding its long context window, multimodal reasoning capabilities and impressive overall performance incredibly useful.We know from user feedback that some applications need lower latency and a lower cost to serve. This inspired us to keep innovating, so today, we’re introducing Gemini 1.5 Flash: a model that’s lighter-weight than 1.5 Pro, and designed to be fast and efficient to serve at scale.Both 1.5 Pro and 1.5 Flash are available in public preview with a 1 million token context window in Google AI Studio and Vertex AI. And now, 1.5 Pro is also available with a 2 million token context window via waitlist to developers using the API and to Google Cloud customers.We’re also introducing updates across the Gemini family of models, announcing our next generation of open models, Gemma 2, and sharing progress on the future of AI assistants, with Project Astra.Context lengths of leading foundation models compared with Gemini 1.5’s 2 million token capability1.5 Flash is the newest addition to the Gemini model family and the fastest Gemini model served in the API. It’s optimized for high-volume, high-frequency tasks at scale, is more cost-efficient to serve and features our breakthrough long context window.While it’s a lighter weight model than 1.5 Pro, it’s highly capable of multimodal reasoning across vast amounts of information and delivers impressive quality for its size.The new Gemini 1.5 Flash model is optimized for speed and efficiency, is highly capable of multimodal reasoning and features our breakthrough long context window.1.5 Flash excels at summarization, chat applications, image and video captioning, data extraction from long documents and tables, and more. This is because it’s been trained by 1.5 Pro through a process called “distillation,” where the most essential knowledge and skills from a larger model are transferred to a smaller, more efficient model.Read more about 1.5 Flash in our updated Gemini 1.5 technical report, on the Gemini technology page, and learn about 1.5 Flash’s availability and pricing.Over the last few months, we’ve significantly improved 1.5 Pro, our best model for general performance across a wide range of tasks.Beyond extending its context window to 2 million tokens, we’ve enhanced its code generation, logical reasoning and planning, multi-turn conversation, and audio and image understanding through data and algorithmic advances. We see strong improvements on public and internal benchmarks for each of these tasks.1.5 Pro can now follow increasingly complex and nuanced instructions, including ones that specify product-level behavior involving role, format and style. We’ve improved control over the model’s responses for specific use cases, like crafting the persona and response style of a chat agent or automating workflows through multiple function calls. And we’ve enabled users to steer model behavior by setting system instructions.We added audio understanding in the Gemini API and Google AI Studio, so 1.5 Pro can now reason across image and audio for videos uploaded in Google AI Studio. And we’re now integrating 1.5 Pro into Google products, including Gemini Advanced and in Workspace apps.Read more about 1.5 Pro in our updated Gemini 1.5 technical report and on the Gemini technology page.Gemini Nano is expanding beyond text-only inputs to include images as well. Starting with Pixel, applications using Gemini Nano with Multimodality will be able to understand the world the way people do — not just through text, but also through sight, sound and spoken language.Read more about Gemini 1.0 Nano on Android.Today, we’re also sharing a series of updates to Gemma, our family of open models built from the same research and technology used to create the Gemini models.We’re announcing Gemma 2, our next generation of open models for responsible AI innovation. Gemma 2 has a new architecture designed for breakthrough performance and efficiency, and will be available in new sizes.The Gemma family is also expanding with PaliGemma, our first vision-language model inspired by PaLI-3. And we’ve upgraded our Responsible Generative AI Toolkit with LLM Comparator for evaluating the quality of model responses.Read more on the Developer blog.As part of Google DeepMind’s mission to build AI responsibly to benefit humanity, we’ve always wanted to develop universal AI agents that can be helpful in everyday life. That’s why today, we’re sharing our progress in building the future of AI assistants with Project Astra (advanced seeing and talking responsive agent).To be truly useful, an agent needs to understand and respond to the complex and dynamic world just like people do — and take in and remember what it sees and hears to understand context and take action. It also needs to be proactive, teachable and personal, so users can talk to it naturally and without lag or delay.While we’ve made incredible progress developing AI systems that can understand multimodal information, getting response time down to something conversational is a difficult engineering challenge. Over the past few years, we’ve been working to improve how our models perceive, reason and converse to make the pace and quality of interaction feel more natural.Building on Gemini, we’ve developed prototype agents that can process information faster by continuously encoding video frames, combining the video and speech input into a timeline of events, and caching this information for efficient recall.By leveraging our leading speech models, we also enhanced how they sound, giving the agents a wider range of intonations. These agents can better understand the context they’re being used in, and respond quickly, in conversation.With technology like this, it’s easy to envision a future where people could have an expert AI assistant by their side, through a phone or glasses. And some of these capabilities are coming to Google products, like the Gemini app and web experience, later this year.We’ve made incredible progress so far with our family of Gemini models, and we’re always striving to advance the state-of-the-art even further. By investing in a relentless production line of innovation, we’re able to explore new ideas at the frontier, while also unlocking the possibility of new and exciting Gemini use cases.Learn more about Gemini and its capabilities. Your information will be used in accordance with Google’s privacy policy.</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>      Done. Just one step more.
    
      Check your inbox to confirm your subscription.
    You are already subscribed to our newsletter.
    You can also subscribe with a
    different email address
    
    .
    
  Let’s stay in touch. Get the latest news from Google in your inbox.
          Follow Us
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We’re sharing updates across our Gemini family of models and a glimpse of Project Astra, our vision for the future of AI assistants.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</title><link href="https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog"/><published>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</updated><id>https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/"><![CDATA[<h3>External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</h3> <p>If you prefer publishing blog posts on medium.com or other external sources, starting version v0.5.0, <a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio">al-folio</a> lets you to display your external posts in the blog feed of your website! 🎉🎉</p> <p>Configuring external sources of super simple. After upgrading to v0.5.0, just add the following section to your _config.yml:</p> <pre>external_sources:<br />  - name: medium.com  # name of the source (arbitrary string)<br />    rss_url: <a href="https://medium.com/@al-folio/feed">https://medium.com/@&lt;your-medium-username&gt;/feed</a></pre> <p>The example above adds your medium.com blog post feed as an external source. But you can add arbitrary RSS feeds as sources.</p> <p>Any questions or suggestions? 👉 Start <a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio/discussions">a discussion on GitHub</a>!</p> <p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;postId=b60a1d241a0a" width="1" height="1" alt=""/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>