<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://benjaminguinet.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://benjaminguinet.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-08-05T14:26:43+00:00</updated><id>https://benjaminguinet.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html"></title><link href="https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2025/2025-05-08-Pop-science-Measles-Rinderpest_evolution/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title=""/><published>2025-08-05T14:26:43+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-05T14:26:43+00:00</updated><id>https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2025/2025-05-08-Pop-science-Measles-Rinderpest_evolution</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2025/2025-05-08-Pop-science-Measles-Rinderpest_evolution/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction"><strong>Introduction</strong></h2> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Main_Measle_rinderpest-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Main_Measle_rinderpest-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Main_Measle_rinderpest-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Main_Measle_rinderpest.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Measles and rinderpest are two viral diseases that have left a profound mark on history : one through its devastating toll on children’s health, which persists worldwide today, and the other through massive economic losses inflicted on livestock farming across many regions. At first glance, these viruses may seem entirely distinct, yet they surprisingly share a relatively recent common ancestor.</p> <p>Around 3,000 years ago, an ancestor of the rinderpest virus made the leap across species and adapted to humans, eventually evolving into the measles virus. Since that pivotal moment, each virus has followed its own evolutionary path: measles with human populations, and rinderpest with livestock.</p> <p>In this article, we’ll delve into their intertwined origins, trace the separate journeys these viruses have taken, and examine how humanity has succeeded in eradicating one, while the other continues to pose significant challenges today. Ultimately, we’ll explore how the lessons learned from defeating one viral foe might hold the key to overcoming the other.</p> <h2 id="rinderpest"><strong>Rinderpest</strong></h2> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG1_MEASLE_RINDERPEST_ILLUSTRATION-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG1_MEASLE_RINDERPEST_ILLUSTRATION-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG1_MEASLE_RINDERPEST_ILLUSTRATION-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG1_MEASLE_RINDERPEST_ILLUSTRATION.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Let’s start with a virus that was once feared in the agricultural world: the rinderpest virus. This virus was infecting cattle but could also infect more than 40 other species of artiodactyls (even-toed ungulates)(Morens et al. 2011). Rinderpest was one of the most devastating animal diseases in history. In some epidemics, it decimated up to 90–100% of infected herds, causing millions of cattle deaths worldwide. Its extreme virulence made it a real health and economic disaster. The disease was transmitted through close contact between animals, via respiratory, oral or faecal secretions. After an incubation period of 8 to 11 days, symptoms appeared: fever, mouth ulcers, followed by severe and often fatal diarrhea.</p> <p>In the 18th century, Europe was hit hard. With no vaccine available at the time, drastic measures were implemented: quarantines, isolation, mass slaughter and disinfection. Thanks to these efforts, the disease was finally eradicated from Europe at the end of the 19th century (Vicq-d’Azyr, 1776).</p> <p>But elsewhere, rinderpest continued to wreak havoc. In Africa, it triggered a catastrophic pandemic, killing millions of animals, causing a major economic crisis, and exacerbating poverty, malnutrition, and human disease (Morens 2003; Wilkinson 1984)</p> <h3 id="a-global-victory-thanks-to-the-vaccine">A global victory thanks to the vaccine</h3> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG2_MEASLE_RINDERPEST_STAMP-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG2_MEASLE_RINDERPEST_STAMP-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG2_MEASLE_RINDERPEST_STAMP-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG2_MEASLE_RINDERPEST_STAMP.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>It was not until the 1920s that the first attenuated vaccine was developed, and then the 1950s before a more effective vaccine enabled mass vaccination campaigns, thanks in particular to a coordinated programme between African countries: Joint Programme-15. As a reminder, a vaccine trains our immune system to recognise a pathogen without causing disease. It contains an attenuated or inactivated form of the microbe, or an antigen (often a protein). As a result, our body learns to defend itself. And if the pathogen appears later, the immune system reacts quickly and neutralises the infection. After the programme’s success until the 1970s, the premature cessation of vaccination led to a resurgence of the virus in Africa, Asia and the Middle East. The WHO responded with several global campaigns (PARC, PACE, GREP, etc.). After decades of international cooperation, the last reported outbreak of rinderpest occurred in Kenya in 2001; however, a 10-year period of active surveillance was necessary before global eradication could be declared in 2011, making it the second virus to be eradicated in history, after smallpox (1980). Today, almost all of the samples still present in laboratories, if any remain, are nothing more than pathological remnants, preserved for research or scientific memory purposes, but having lost all infectious capacity (Butler 2019). Ultimately, rinderpest not only devastated livestock, it also played an important role in the early history of infectious disease science. It helped inspire one of the earliest theories on the spread of disease (Morens 2003) and even led to the development of a vaccination plan (Anderson and McKay 1994). Scientists studying rinderpest were also the first to demonstrate that mothers could pass on their immunity to their offspring (Huygelen 1997). The global alarm raised by its ravages ultimately led to the creation of the World Organisation for Animal Health (OIE) in 1924.</p> <h2 id="measles-a-human-cousin-of-rinderpest-">Measles: a human cousin of rinderpest :</h2> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG3_MEASLE_MEASLE_ILLUSTRATION-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG3_MEASLE_MEASLE_ILLUSTRATION-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG3_MEASLE_MEASLE_ILLUSTRATION-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG3_MEASLE_MEASLE_ILLUSTRATION.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Let us now turn our attention to measles. Like its cousin rinderpest, it is an RNA virus of the Morbillivirus genus, meaning it has a very high mutation rate, giving it the ability to rapidly explore the space of possibilities in order to adapt to its host. However, we will see that in the case of rinderpest and measles, although they mutate rapidly, they tend to remain relatively stable over time. As we saw above, measles is actually the result of a species jump. In 2020, researchers traced the history of the measles virus from ancient samples (including the lung of a child who died in 1912) (Düx et al. 2020). Their study shows that around 2,000 to 3,000 years ago (roughly when Buddha was living in South Asia and shortly before the birth of Socrates), a bovine virus accidentally found its way into the bodies of unsuspecting humans and then split into two strains: one became measles in humans, the other became rinderpest in cattle. But why did this species jump occur at precisely this time, and why did it end up establishing itself permanently in humans?</p> <h3 id="when-human-density-becomes-a-condition-for-a-virus-to-survive"><strong>When human density becomes a condition for a virus to survive</strong></h3> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG4_MEASLES_Morbivirus_phylogeny-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG4_MEASLES_Morbivirus_phylogeny-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG4_MEASLES_Morbivirus_phylogeny-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG4_MEASLES_Morbivirus_phylogeny.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>For a virus such as measles to survive long-term in a human population, one essential condition must be met: population density. Measles is an extremely contagious virus that confers lifelong immunity to those who have contracted it. This means that in order to continue circulating, the virus constantly needs new susceptible individuals to infect, particularly children who have never been exposed to it before.</p> <p>However, in Neolithic, Bronze Age and even early Iron Age human societies, human groups were still too small and too scattered. Villages were modest, towns were embryonic, and exchanges between communities were limited (Brozio et al. 2024). Even if an ancestral measles virus had crossed the species barrier at that time, it would have hit a wall: without new victims, it would have quickly disappeared. Its rapid transmission, combined with the lasting immunity it confers, prevents its survival in small populations.</p> <h4 id="cities-large-enough-to-fuel-the-epidemic"><strong>Cities large enough to fuel the epidemic</strong></h4> <p>It was only at the end of the first millennium BCE that conditions changed decisively. Thanks to agricultural, commercial and political advances, large cities capable of housing between 250,000 and 500,000 inhabitants began to appear in certain regions of the world, notably in South Asia, China, the Near East, North Africa and Europé (Clark 2014; Inoue et al. 2015). This threshold is crucial: it represents the critical mass necessary for measles to be transmitted continuously, from one generation to the next, without dying out (Düx et al. 2020).</p> <p>From that point on, one of these zoonotic jumps, a bovine virus infecting a human, found a favourable environment. In these larger, interconnected societies, the virus was able to maintain itself, evolve and adapt to its new host. It then became a fully-fledged human virus, giving rise to the measles we know today, an endemic virus deeply linked to the history of great civilisations.</p> <h2 id="why-has-measles-not-yet-been-eradicated"><strong>Why has measles not yet been eradicated?</strong></h2> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG5_MEASLE_PARTICULES-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG5_MEASLE_PARTICULES-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG5_MEASLE_PARTICULES-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG5_MEASLE_PARTICULES.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Unlike rinderpest, measles still exists. And yet, the current vaccine (MMRV), which has been in use since the 1960s, remains extremely effective (Bankamp et al. 2011; Zemella et al. 2024). In fact, despite the fact that the measles virus is an RNA virus and therefore, in theory, subject to a high mutation rate, it exhibits remarkable antigenic stability. This paradox can be explained by a key biological phenomenon: the measles virus is antigenically monotypic. In other words, the virus’s surface proteins, particularly haemagglutinin (H), which is the main target of the neutralising immune response, are extremely conserved over time and across the various circulating strains (Fulton et al. 2015). This antigenic stability can be explained in part by strong structural and functional constraints: the virus’s surface proteins cannot vary greatly without compromising their ability to interact effectively with the host’s cell receptors. In other words, the virus cannot ‘afford’ to change too much without losing its ability to infect. This contrasts sharply with viruses such as influenza, whose surface proteins evolve rapidly under immune pressure, requiring annual vaccine reformulation.</p> <p>When an individual naturally contracts measles and survives, they generally acquire lifelong immunity. This means that it is highly unlikely that they will be reinfected later in life, and no additional doses of vaccine are necessary. Vaccination, on the other hand, confers this immunity without exposing the individual to the risks associated with natural infection. Furthermore, researchers have recently shown that measles infection can cause a form of ‘memory loss’ in the immune system, reducing its ability to remember pathogens it has encountered before. This phenomenon has not been observed in vaccinated children, further highlighting the importance of vaccination (Mina et al. 2019). Two doses of the vaccine are recommended to ensure immunity and prevent epidemics, as not all children develop immunity after the first dose.</p> <p>Hence, like rinderpest, this virus has not evolved into new serotypes like influenza, making its eradication technically possible.</p> <h3 id="-so-why-are-we-failing">** So why are we failing?**</h3> <p>The answer can be summed up in one word: human resources.</p> <p>Unlike cattle, which cannot refuse an injection, human beings have that choice. However, this free will can be influenced by many factors: lack of information, mistrust of science, unequal access to healthcare, political tensions, etc. These issues have been exacerbated by events related to the COVID-19 pandemic, which have contributed to increased scepticism and mistrust of vaccines among some members of the public (Lazarus et al. 2023).</p> <p>This crisis of confidence has worrying consequences, including a reversal of progress in public health. In 2019, for example, the United States, where measles had been officially eliminated since 2000, experienced a resurgence of outbreaks in certain communities with low vaccination rates. For example, the proportion of children who received a first dose of measles vaccine was 83% in 2023, well below the 86% level reached in 2019.</p> <p>The CDC sounded the alarm:</p> <p><em>«The current increase in measles cases is deeply concerning. The United States is once again at risk of losing its measles elimination status due to declining vaccination coverage in certain communities.»</em> (CDC, 2019)</p> <p>Peter Hotez, a public health expert, summed up the situation as follows:</p> <p><em>«Measles is the canary in the coal mine for vaccine-preventable diseases. When it resurges, it’s a sign of broader systemic failure in public health infrastructure and trust.»</em> (Hotez, 2021)</p> <h3 id="-the-issue-goes-beyond-medicine">** The issue goes beyond medicine**</h3> <p>Measles is a good example of how fighting a virus is not just a matter of vaccination, but also of communication, social justice, logistics and trust in science. Even with an excellent vaccine, a lack of coordination or will can ruin all efforts.</p> <p>Even today, despite massive campaigns by the WHO, Gavi and UNICEF, more than 107,000 children died of measles in 2023, a completely preventable disease that has already saved the lives of nearly 60 million people between 2000 and 2023.</p> <p><strong>In conclusion:</strong> We should learn from the past and protect the future. The eradication of rinderpest, although little known to the general public, is a major victory for science, cooperation and international solidarity. It shows that the impossible becomes possible when resources, will and science come together. Measles, on the other hand, reminds us that negligence can turn everything upside down.</p> <p><em>«The resurgence of preventable diseases like measles is a wake-up call. We must protect progress through sustained investment in vaccines and trust in science.»</em></p> <p>— Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus, Director-General of the WHO (2022)</p> <p>Health, whether human or animal, is a fragile common good that must always be defended</p> <p><strong>References</strong></p> <p>Anderson, J., and J. A. McKay. 1994. “The Detection of Antibodies against Peste Des Petits Ruminants Virus in Cattle, Sheep and Goats and the Possible Implications to Rinderpest Control Programmes.” Epidemiology and Infection 112 (1): 225–31.</p> <p>Bankamp, Bettina, Makoto Takeda, Yan Zhang, Wenbo Xu, and Paul A. Rota. 2011. “Genetic Characterization of Measles Vaccine Strains.” The Journal of Infectious Diseases 204 Suppl 1 (suppl_1): S533-48.</p> <p>Brozio, Jan Piet, Jutta Kneisel, Stefanie Schaefer-Di Maida, Julian Laabs, Ingo Feeser, Artur Ribeiro, and Sebastian Schultrich. 2024. “Patterns of Socio-Economic Cultural Transformations in Neolithic and Bronze Age Societies in the Central Northern European Plain.” In Perspectives on Socio-Environmental Transformations in Ancient Europe, 105–42. Cham: Springer Nature Switzerland.</p> <p>Butler, Declan. 2019. “Sequence and Destroy: The Quest to Eliminate the Last Stocks of Deadly Rinderpest Virus.” Nature 572 (7767): 18.</p> <p>Clark, Gregory. 2014. “Ian Morris. The Measure of Civilization: How Social Development Decides the Fate of Nations.” The American Historical Review 119 (3): 824–26.</p> <p>Düx, Ariane, Sebastian Lequime, Livia Victoria Patrono, Bram Vrancken, Sengül Boral, Jan F. Gogarten, Antonia Hilbig, et al. 2020. “Measles Virus and Rinderpest Virus Divergence Dated to the Sixth Century BCE.” Science (New York, N.Y.) 368 (6497): 1367–70.</p> <p>Fulton, Benjamin O., David Sachs, Shannon M. Beaty, Sohui T. Won, Benhur Lee, Peter Palese, and Nicholas S. Heaton. 2015. “Mutational Analysis of Measles Virus Suggests Constraints on Antigenic Variation of the Glycoproteins.” Cell Reports 11 (9): 1331–38.</p> <p>Huygelen, C. 1997. “The Immunization of Cattle against Rinderpest in Eighteenth-Century Europe.” Medical History 41 (2): 182–96.</p> <p>Inoue, Hiroko, Alexis Álvarez, Eugene N. Anderson, Andrew Owen, Rebecca Álvarez, Kirk Lawrence, and Christopher Chase-Dunn. 2015. “Urban Scale Shifts since the Bronze Age: Upsweeps, Collapses, and Semiperipheral Development.” Social Science History 39 (2): 175–200.</p> <p>Lazarus, Jeffrey V., Katarzyna Wyka, Trenton M. White, Camila A. Picchio, Lawrence O. Gostin, Heidi J. Larson, Kenneth Rabin, Scott C. Ratzan, Adeeba Kamarulzaman, and Ayman El-Mohandes. 2023. “A Survey of COVID-19 Vaccine Acceptance across 23 Countries in 2022.” Nature Medicine 29 (2): 366–75.</p> <p>Mina, Michael J., Tomasz Kula, Yumei Leng, Mamie Li, Rory D. de Vries, Mikael Knip, Heli Siljander, et al. 2019. “Measles Virus Infection Diminishes Preexisting Antibodies That Offer Protection from Other Pathogens.” Science (New York, N.Y.) 366 (6465): 599–606.</p> <p>Morens, David M. 2003. “Characterizing a ‘New’ Disease: Epizootic and Epidemic Anthrax, 1769-1780.” American Journal of Public Health 93 (6): 886–93.</p> <p>Morens, David M., Edward C. Holmes, A. Sally Davis, and Jeffery K. Taubenberger. 2011. “Global Rinderpest Eradication: Lessons Learned and Why Humans Should Celebrate Too.” The Journal of Infectious Diseases 204 (4): 502–5.</p> <p>Wilkinson, L. 1984. “Rinderpest and Mainstream Infectious Disease Concepts in the Eighteenth Century.” Medical History 28 (2): 129–50.</p> <p>Zemella, Anne, Kerstin Beer, Franziska Ramm, Dana Wenzel, Ariane Düx, Kevin Merkel, Sebastien Calvignac-Spencer, et al. 2024. “Vaccine-Induced Neutralizing Antibodies Bind to the H Protein of a Historical Measles Virus.” International Journal of Medical Microbiology: IJMM 314 (151607): 151607.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">Sexual selection, from sexy dancing to cheating, anything goes!</title><link href="https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2025/Pop-science-Sexual_selection/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sexual selection, from sexy dancing to cheating, anything goes!"/><published>2025-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2025/Pop-science-Sexual_selection</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2025/Pop-science-Sexual_selection/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction"><strong>Introduction</strong></h2> <p>Watching a wildlife documentary or simply taking a walk in the woods, you’re bound to have come across an animal with extravagant characteristics. So extravagant, in fact, that you might well wonder whether it doesn’t go against natural selection. Take, for example, a peacock’s bulky tail, the enormous fins of a fighting fish or a deer’s impressive antlers. They’re beautiful ornaments, yes, but they’re also very awkward to move around on and highly visible to predators! The question then arises: how can such features be selected when they seem to have a negative impact on the survival of the individuals that wear them?</p> <p>The answer lies in a concept that I’m about to introduce to you: sexual selection. In the rest of this article, we’ll look at why, in the vast majority of species, females choose males and how they choose them.</p> <p>We will then look at other non-human animals to understand some of the strategies that have been selected over the course of evolution to persuade females to mate. We’ll see that there are cheats in the animal world and that sometimes strength and beauty are no match for some clever little buggers!</p> <h2 id="sexual-selection-a-story-about-sex"><strong>Sexual selection, a story about sex</strong></h2> <p>What we remember from the concept of natural selection developed by Darwin and Wallace (more details in our article on this subject) is that individuals with the most adaptive characteristics survive better, reproduce better and are therefore selected from generation to generation. However, if you’re an observer of nature, you should be able to spot an inconsistency in all these stories… In fact, if you look closely at the animal world, you’ll see that males and females sometimes have different phenotypes. Males are often more colourful or have flashy ornaments. Females generally have more discreet attributes. In terms of the theory of natural selection, it seems counter-intuitive that individuals should be selected when they are sporting multicoloured coats that make them more visible to predators and make them look very cluttered.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2_BAS_ornements-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2_BAS_ornements-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2_BAS_ornements-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/2_BAS_ornements.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>But were Darwin and Wallace wrong? What’s the point of favouring such disabling characteristics that increase the probability of dying? Well, the answer can be summed up in one simple phrase: to gain access to reproduction!</p> <p>Both knew that natural selection could not be expected to favour the evolution of disadvantageous traits. Although they had differing ideas on the subject, they were nevertheless able to offer a solution to this problem: sexual selection. In his book ‘The descent of man and selection in relation to sex’[1] published in 1874, Darwin proposed a new evolutionary process different from natural selection. This process does not depend on a struggle for existence in relation to other organisms or environmental conditions, but on a struggle between individuals of one sex for possession of the other sex.</p> <h3 id="definition-of-sexual-selection-">Definition of sexual selection :</h3> <p><em>Sexual selection is a theory according to which the evolution of certain remarkable physical traits such as pronounced colouring, increased size or striking ornamentation in animals can make it easier for those who possess them to obtain mates.</em></p> <h2 id="an-explanation-for-the-war-of-the-sexes-anisogamy"><strong>An explanation for the war of the sexes: anisogamy</strong></h2> <p>But why is it that, in the majority of cases, it’s the males who end up with the extra ornaments!</p> <p>The most widespread theory to explain this phenomenon is anisogamy. ‘Anisos’ means non-equal and ‘gamos’ means marriage. Anisogamy therefore refers to a form of fertilisation in which the gametes of the two sexes differ, particularly in size.</p> <p>The male gametes (spermatozoa) are much smaller than the female gametes (oocytes). In humans, an oocyte measures around 120µm whereas a spermatozoon measures around 50µm. In addition, there is a significant difference in production cost between a male gamete and a female gamete. Oocytes live longer and contain nutritional resources, but are more ‘expensive’ (metabolically) to produce.</p> <p>The main idea behind this theory is that males produce more and cheaper gametes. Females have only a limited and precious supply. This imbalance will lead to sexual conflict. Females have an interest in carefully choosing a male, while males have an interest in fertilising as many females as possible.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/3_anisogamie-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/3_anisogamie-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/3_anisogamie-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/3_anisogamie.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Over the course of evolution, this war of the sexes has put males in competition with each other for access to a limited quantity of female gametes, and thus to the much-hoped-for paternity.</p> <p><strong>NB</strong> : it is interesting to ask how anisogamy emerged. But also why there are differentiated sexes. One of the answers lies in the fact that it prevents self-fertilisation. If you’re interested, read <a href="https://sfecologie.org/regard/r78-fev-2018-giraud-billiard-evolution-anisogamie/">this article</a> on the subject.</p> <h2 id="the-cornelian-choice-of-females-between-direct-and-indirect-benefits"><strong>The Cornelian choice of females, between direct and indirect benefits</strong></h2> <p>The males’ objectives are clear. They need females to ensure that they have offspring, and they are competing to get them. What do the females gain and why choose one criterion over another?</p> <p>In some cases it’s quite clear. If we take the example of a female gorilla given the choice between a pudgy gorilla with low social status or a dominant, muscular gorilla, it’s easy to see why she would choose the dominant gorilla. The male probably has access to more food and can protect his territory. The female gains physical security and food. Now, if we take the example of the peacock, it’s a little less intuitive to understand why females prefer the males who do the best cartwheels.</p> <p>The choice of females is based on two main categories of criteria: <strong>direct</strong> and <strong>indirect</strong> advantages.</p> <h2 id="sexual-selection---direct-advantages"><strong>Sexual selection - Direct advantages</strong></h2> <p>A direct advantage will be immediately identifiable by the female and will instantly increase her fertility or lifespan. For example, females can obtain: better access to food, protection from harassing males or help in raising their offspring, or avoid being infected by parasites (or other diseases) by choosing healthy males.</p> <p>Direct benefits can be of various kinds. Some species offer nuptial gifts, which are usually food. This behaviour is found in a wide variety of organisms such as birds, insects and spiders. Sometimes there is a positive correlation between the size of the gift and the copulation time allowed by the female. For example, if the male provides the female with a large prey item, he will be able to transfer more spermatozoa [3,4]. In other species, such as the Red-backed Black Widow, males offer themselves as a <strong>nuptial gift</strong> by allowing themselves to be eaten [5].</p> <p>Another direct and seemingly obvious advantage is choosing a sexual partner who will help raise the young for some species. Females will choose a good father to help them build a nest and feed the young. These behaviours are observed in many bird species, but also in mice.</p> <p>A final example can be found in bullfrogs. Females will prefer males with the ‘best’ territory. The eggs will thus be protected from predators during their development. Sexual selection - Indirect advantages</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/4_BAS_avantages-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/4_BAS_avantages-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/4_BAS_avantages-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/4_BAS_avantages.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="sexual-selection---indirect-advantages"><strong>Sexual selection - Indirect advantages</strong></h2> <p>An indirect advantage is less obvious to the female and can be interpreted as a gamble. The female will have to detect whether a male is a good partner on the basis of clues that are more or less clear (to our human eyes). If she wins her bet, the female will produce healthy offspring who will in turn be able to produce numerous offspring, indirectly increasing the female’s reproductive success.</p> <p>To make her choice, the female will rely on specific signals that will be interpreted as quality indicators. These are often exaggerated physical traits that have been selected in males over the course of evolution. These are called secondary sexual characteristics. There are two complementary theories to explain the appearance of these strange characteristics.</p> <h3 id="when-males-get-carried-away">When males get carried away…</h3> <p><strong>Fisher’s ‘runaway’ theory</strong> proposes that, over the generations, a non-adaptive trait that is visible and guarantees good quality will be selected by the females. A positive feedback loop then follows. Females are increasingly interested in this characteristic, so sexual selection will encourage it to increase.</p> <p>For example, females will choose the males with the longest plumage because their offspring will also inherit long plumage and will in turn be chosen by the females of the next generation, maximising the probability of gene dispersal (Fisher 1930).</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/5_BAS_fisher-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/5_BAS_fisher-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/5_BAS_fisher-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/5_BAS_fisher.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>This mechanism will then lead to unbridled selection for the exaggeration of ornament and preference. This mechanism will continue until the production costs of the ornament exceed the reproductive benefit of possessing it. In theory it could be any non-adaptive trait as long as females can easily compare them. The cost only appears at the final stage of an evolutionary spiral.</p> <h3 id="the-theory-of-handicap-and-good-genes">The theory of handicap and good genes</h3> <p>The alternative theory to Fisherian runaway evolution is called the handicap theory. It is also known as the good genes theory.</p> <p>According to this <strong>handicap theory</strong>, males with extravagant traits that are even dangerous for their survival would be males of good overall quality. Indeed, males disabled by an extravagant trait were able to survive in a hostile environment even though (for example) they had to drag around a huge multicoloured tail (Zahavi 1975). Their extravagant character would therefore be an honest signal about their physical condition and therefore their “good genes”.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/6_BAS_handicap-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/6_BAS_handicap-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/6_BAS_handicap-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/6_BAS_handicap.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>All these mechanisms are based on the supposed existence of genes conferring greater vigour (“good genes” hypothesis), revealed by external handicaps and therefore only able to be developed by individuals of very high individual quality. However, evidence that females select for good genes remains scarce despite decades of studies on mate choice in many organisms. This apparent lack of consensus continues to create debate about the importance of the good gene model in the field of evolutionary biology.</p> <h2 id="what-strategies-do-males-use"><strong>What strategies do males use?</strong></h2> <h3 id="pre-copulatory-behaviour">Pre-copulatory behaviour</h3> <p>Most of the time, when we think of sexual selection, we think of confrontations as the mating season approaches or sumptuous courtship displays. In the animal kingdom, these strategies are widespread and occur before copulation. If these behaviours have been selected over the course of evolution, it’s mainly because they allow the best males to be chosen. Both in terms of <strong>indirect advantage</strong> (if I choose the male who wins, then my offspring will probably also inherit the genes that will enable them to win the competition in turn), or <strong>direct advantage</strong> (if I choose the strongest male, then I increase my probability of survival and that of my offspring because I will be better protected from predators).</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/7_BAS_strategies-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/7_BAS_strategies-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/7_BAS_strategies-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/7_BAS_strategies.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="sperm-competition-sexual-selection-in-detail"><strong>Sperm competition, sexual selection in detail</strong></h2> <p>Females sometimes choose not to put all their eggs in one basket. In these species, they often mate with different males to maximise their chances of having healthy offspring. In this situation, the competition between males takes place at sperm level and is called sperm competition.</p> <p>Males have no interest in other males impregnating the female with whom they have just mated. Thus, in the course of evolution, multiple strategies have emerged at different times during the copulatory stage.</p> <h3 id="before-copulation-the-hunter-loses-his-place">Before copulation, the hunter loses his place</h3> <p>In some species (such as dragonflies), when the female has already been fertilised, the next male may take several hours to clean the female’s spermatic cavity before introducing his seed. In this way, using small feather dusters, he eliminates the sperm of any predecessors and increases his own chances of paternity.</p> <h3 id="during-copulation">During copulation</h3> <p>In order to prolong the copulation period, some males will not let go of the female an inch. The aim is to maximise the chances of their sperm being fertilised during mating. To achieve this, some males act as copulatory plugs. In some phasms, genital contact can last up to 79 days! [10].</p> <h3 id="after-copulation">After copulation</h3> <p><strong>Obstruction of the genital tract</strong>: Some species (cockroaches, locusts and other insects) will accompany their sperm with a substance (cement glands) designed to obstruct the female’s genital tract during subsequent mating (e.g. dung flies).</p> <p><strong>Induced contraception</strong>: Another strategy consists of releasing a substance that prevents subsequent mating. In mosquitoes, males produce a substance through their secondary sex gland that inhibits the receptivity of inseminated females. As a result, they refuse most matings with other males [11].</p> <p><strong>Guarding females</strong>: Others will simply keep their eyes on the females and keep away any males likely to want to impregnate the female [3], as in the case of certain monkeys or mallard ducks.</p> <p><strong>Ugly beauty</strong>: Another tactic is to make females unattractive to other males. This phenomenon is particularly well known in moths. Males deposit anti-aphrodisiacs on females during mating [3].</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/8_competition_spermatique-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/8_competition_spermatique-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/8_competition_spermatique-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/8_competition_spermatique.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="the-animal-world-is-full-of-cheats"><strong>The animal world is full of cheats!</strong></h2> <p>So far we’ve seen that secondary sexual characteristics (for example, the peacock’s tail) were honest indicators of the underlying quality of the males. The costs associated with producing and maintaining these extravagant features informed the females about the overall health of the males that wore them. The more physically fit a male is, the more access he has to quality energy resources. And the more he is able to waste them strutting around the forest with a very long tail. Some males have seen this as an opportunity to optimise their energy allocation by reducing certain costs associated with secondary sexual traits without damaging their overall reproductive success. This is where cheating comes in!</p> <h3 id="examples-of-cheaters">Examples of cheaters</h3> <p>Some male spiders fill their nuptial gifts with silk instead of prey to fool females and reproduce for longer [14].</p> <p>As they are unable to compete with the larger males, some will trick the females into fertilisation all the same. In some amphibians, the smaller males will closely follow the larger males and grab the females attracted to them.</p> <p>The males of other fish species will take advantage of fertilisation by throwing sperm into the water to mix theirs with that of other fish. In some beetles, the males will fertilise the females in secret while a larger male stands guard.</p> <p>Finally, many females choose males who will give up all their time to help with feeding or defend the territory. The males thus find themselves torn between staying with the female and impregnating as many females as possible. As a result, it is not uncommon to observe males sneaking off to impregnate other females. A study of birds, the Prothonotary Warbler, showed that nearly 27% of offspring were identified as the result of extra-pair mating [15]!</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/9_BAS_tricheries-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/9_BAS_tricheries-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/9_BAS_tricheries-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/9_BAS_tricheries.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="a-final-word"><strong>A final word</strong></h2> <p>Historically, the field of sexual selection is still very young. Indeed, research in this field only began in the 1960s [22]. So it’s not surprising that the concept of sexual selection remains little known, even though the general public is already familiar with natural selection.</p> <p>Science is not neutral. Scientists are caught up in an axiological matrix from which they cannot free themselves, and from which it is undesirable for them to free themselves, as this would deprive science of its human dimension. It is wrong to think that when a scientist puts down his hat and coat and puts on his white coat, he removes the interpretative filter between us and reality.</p> <p>So we need to remain cautious about the observations we make about the world around us. Although we can have very serious studies on the subject, the fact remains that our perception of things is subjective, especially in a world as complex as ours. The idea of a common value is difficult to maintain. So now, more than ever, we need to share the knowledge and viewpoints of a diversity of researchers on a research topic, because that’s how we can minimise our personal interpretations.</p> <h2 id="back-to-the-article"><strong>Back to the article</strong></h2> <p>In this article we have just seen a few examples that I have chosen, but in reality there are as many differences as there are species. I haven’t even mentioned species that don’t reproduce sexually or those in which the sex changes over the course of an individual’s life (but that’s only part of the story)! Personally, I’m still fascinated by all the singularities that surround us, especially as sexuality in general shapes and occupies a key place in evolutionary processes: the passing on of genes!</p> <p><a href="https://www.projetpangolin.com/la-selection-sexuelle/">French version</a></p> <p><strong>Illustrations:</strong> Vincent Lhuillier &amp; Salomé Bourg <strong>Reviewing:</strong> The Project Pangolin team</p> <p><strong>References</strong></p> <p>1- Darwin, C., 1875. The Descent of Man, and Selection in relation to Sex. Nature, 11(277)</p> <p>2- T, A., 2021. R78 : Pourquoi des sexes différents, et pourquoi deux le plus souvent? par T. Giraud et S. Billiard - sfecologie.org.</p> <p>3- Albo, M. and Peretti, A., 2015. Worthless and Nutritive Nuptial Gifts: Mating Duration, Sperm Stored and Potential Female Decisions in Spiders. PLOS ONE, 10(6)</p> <p>4- Gwynne, D., 2008. Sexual Conflict over Nuptial Gifts in Insects. Annual Review of Entomology, 53(1)</p> <p>5- Andrade, M., 1998. Female hunger can explain variation in cannibalistic behavior despite male sacrifice in redback spiders. Behavioral Ecology, 9(1)</p> <p>6- Toft, S. and Albo, M., 2016. The shield effect: nuptial gifts protect males against pre-copulatory sexual cannibalism. Biology Letters, 12(5)</p> <p>7- Cecie Starr and Ralph Taggart, Biology – the Unity and Diversity of Life, 6th Ed., Wadsworth Publishing Company, 1992</p> <p>8- Edward T. Hall, The Hidden Dimension, New York, Anchor Books, 1966</p> <p>9- Córdoba-Aguilar, A., Uhía, E. and Rivera, A., 2003. Sperm competition in Odonata (Insecta): the evolution of female sperm storage and rivals’ sperm displacement. Journal of Zoology, 261(4)</p> <p>10- Gangrade, G., 1964. Accessory glands of female phasmid, Necroscia sparaxes Westwood. Annals and Magazine of Natural History, 7(84)</p> <p>11- Helinski, M., et al., 2012. Duration and dose-dependency of female sexual receptivity responses to seminal fluid proteins in Aedes albopictus and Ae. aegypti mosquitoes. Journal of Insect Physiology, 58(10)</p> <p>12- Parker, G., 1970. Sperm competition and its evolutionary consequences in the insects. Biological Reviews, 45(4)</p> <p>13- van Noordwijk, A. and de Jong, G., 1986. Acquisition and Allocation of Resources: Their Influence on Variation in Life History Tactics. The American Naturalist, 128(1)</p> <p>14 - Ghislandi, P., et al., 2017. Silk wrapping of nuptial gifts aids cheating behaviour in male spiders. Behavioral Ecology, 28(3)</p> <p>15 – Morton Catherine Heidrich Virginia., 2013. PhD thesis. Who’s Your Daddy? A Study of Extra-Pair Copulation and Mating Behaviors of Protonotaria citrea Behaviors of Protonotaria citrea.</p> <p>16 - Sinervo, B. and Lively, C., 1996. The rock–paper–scissors game and the evolution of alternative male strategies. Nature, 380(6571)</p> <p>17- Puts, D., 2021. Human sexual selection. 20015. Current Opinion in Psychology.</p> <p>18- Scott, I., et al., 2014. Human preferences for sexually dimorphic faces may be evolutionarily novel. PNAS, 111(40)</p> <p>19- Wheatley, J.,et al., 2014. Women’s faces and voices are cues to reproductive potential in industrial and forager societies. Evolution and Human Behavior, 35(4)</p> <p>20- Collins, S. and Missing, C., 2003. Vocal and visual attractiveness are related in women. Animal Behaviour, 65(5)</p> <p>21- Singh, D., et al., 2010. Cross-cultural consensus for waist–hip ratio and women’s attractiveness. Evolution and Human Behavior, 31(3)</p> <p>22- Giraldeau, L., Cézilly, F. and Danchin, E., 2005. Écologie comportementale. Paris: Dunod.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="pop-science"/><category term="Sexual"/><category term="selection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Popular scientific paper]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Natural Selection</title><link href="https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2025/Pop-science_Natural_selection/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Natural Selection"/><published>2025-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2025/Pop-science_Natural_selection</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2025/Pop-science_Natural_selection/"><![CDATA[<p>Has your mind ever been stirred by the sight of an eagle swooping down on its prey, or a giraffe whose remarkably long neck seems perfectly suited to the height of the trees? If so, you’ve already begun to wonder how such wonders of nature came to be. Part of the answer lies in the powerful concept of natural selection.</p> <p>To explore this idea together, I invite you to embark on a journey:</p> <ul> <li> <p>First, we’ll travel back in time to revisit the early thoughts of our ancestors.</p> </li> <li> <p>Then, we’ll dive into the heart of the matter and unravel the mechanisms behind the theory known as natural selection.</p> </li> <li> <p>We’ll see how chance, guided by nature, can endow certain species with astonishing abilities.</p> </li> <li> <p>And to fully convince you, we’ll examine a striking example of evolution that unfolds within a single human lifetime.</p> </li> </ul> <p>Finally, we’ll take a look at some of the key controversies that have shaped the history of this groundbreaking theory.</p> <h2 id="so-what-exactly-is-evolution"><strong>So, what exactly is evolution?</strong></h2> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG1_NS-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG1_NS-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG1_NS-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG1_NS.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>In biology, evolution refers to the change in characteristics of a given species over multiple generations — such as the shape of a bird’s beak or the development of limbs in tetrapods. This process is driven by several evolutionary mechanisms.</p> <p>Among these, natural selection is undoubtedly the most well-known and extensively studied by scientists — and it’s precisely this concept that we’ll explore in this article.</p> <h2 id="the-story-of-a-theory-natural-selection"><strong>The Story of a Theory: Natural Selection</strong></h2> <p>I hope you’ll forgive me for not recounting the entire history of natural selection here! Instead, I’ll focus on some of the key milestones along the way. 🙂</p> <p>Like all scientific disciplines, evolutionary biology has its own philosophical roots — and its story begins in ancient times.</p> <h3 id="it-all-begins-in-antiquity"><strong>It All Begins in Antiquity</strong></h3> <p>As early as Antiquity, philosophers such as Plato and Aristotle were already pondering the nature and place of living beings in the world. Aristotle even developed an early system of animal classification known as the <em>Scala Naturae</em> — or “Great Chain of Being.”</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG2_NS-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG2_NS-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG2_NS-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG2_NS.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Aristotle’s idea was based on the belief that living beings could be ranked on a hierarchical scale according to their degree of “perfection.” At the top of this Scala Naturae were the angels, with humans placed just beneath them. All other creatures occupied progressively lower rungs of the ladder [1].</p> <p>Later on, Aristotle’s thinking became intertwined with Christian theology. In medieval Europe, it was widely believed that each species had been individually created by a divine being. Furthermore, it was thought that species were fixed — unchanging over time.</p> <p>Over the centuries, however, a growing number of scientists became captivated by the incredible diversity of life. Motivated by curiosity and wonder, they began to describe the natural world in increasing detail.</p> <h3 id="natural-selection-in-the-modern-era"><strong>Natural Selection in the Modern Era</strong></h3> <p>Between 1600 and 1800, the idea that “the path to God lies through the contemplation of His works” became deeply influential. This belief inspired much of the early work in natural history, leading to ambitious efforts to classify the living world. Yet a major challenge persisted: how should life forms be grouped and defined?</p> <p>In the 18th century, the Swedish botanist Carl von Linné (Linnaeus) proposed the concept of the species as the basic unit of classification. He introduced a hierarchical system that grouped organisms based on structural similarities: Species, Genus, Family, Order, Class, Phylum, and Kingdom [2].</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG3_NS-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG3_NS-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG3_NS-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG3_NS.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Linnaeus classified species as if they were fixed and unchanging — in other words, as if evolution didn’t occur. But occasional hybrids between species (a phenomenon well known to dog breeders, for instance) hinted that the boundaries between species might not be as rigid as once believed.</p> <p>Over time, the discovery of fossilized remains further challenged this static view of the natural world. Fossils introduced the radical notion that species could go extinct [3]. During the Enlightenment, naturalists began to distance themselves from strictly religious interpretations of the natural sciences. A shift in thinking was underway: species might actually change over time!</p> <h3 id="lamarcks-evolutionary-theory"><strong>Lamarck’s Evolutionary Theory</strong></h3> <p>In the early 19th century, French naturalist Jean-Baptiste Lamarck was the first to propose a full-fledged theory of organic evolution [4]. His goal was to explain what an animal is — how it forms, how it functions, and how it might change. According to Lamarck, living organisms had the ability to respond — we would now say “adapt” — to changes in their environment. These physical changes were driven by an internal “vital force” and could be passed down from one generation to the next through a process later called the inheritance of acquired characteristics.</p> <p>To understand this theory, let’s look at a classic example: the long neck of the giraffe. Lamarck proposed that giraffes originally had necks similar in length to those of other animals [1]. But to reach the leaves high in acacia trees, they had to stretch — and stretch — and stretch. Over the course of their lives, this repeated effort gradually lengthened their necks. These changes were then passed on to their offspring, who continued the trend, eventually resulting in the long-necked giraffes we see today.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG4_NS-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG4_NS-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG4_NS-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG4_NS.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Despite the revolutionary nature of Lamarck’s theory<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, the evolutionary mechanisms he proposed — collectively known as transformism — were far from convincing. And you’ve probably already spotted the issue! Just because one of your parents took up bodybuilding before you were conceived doesn’t mean you’re going to inherit all their hard-earned muscles!</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG5_NS-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG5_NS-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG5_NS-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG5_NS.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h4 id="what-about-epigenetics"><strong>What About Epigenetics?</strong></h4> <p>I won’t wade into the current debate around the supposed revival of Lamarckian ideas in light of recent discoveries in epigenetics (i.e., the inheritance of traits not directly encoded in genes). But it’s worth noting that, since the 1990s, solid evidence has accumulated in several species — especially plants, nematodes, and insects — showing that epigenetic inheritance can, in some cases, mimic genetic inheritance, albeit in a less stable manner (see [5,6] for a more detailed discussion and [7] for a critical perspective on the analogy).</p> <h3 id="charles-and-russell-evolutions-headliners"><strong>Charles and Russell: Evolution’s Headliners</strong></h3> <p>Although evolutionary ideas had circulated for centuries, it wasn’t until the work of Charles Darwin and Alfred Russel Wallace that biological evolution gained widespread acceptance [8]. In an era still largely shaped by theological thinking, Darwin and Wallace stood out for their rational, evidence-based approach. Unlike their predecessors, they embraced the reality of scientific observations and sought plausible mechanisms to explain how species change over time.</p> <p>The boldness of their work lay in the fact that they offered a coherent, natural explanation for evolution — one that didn’t rely on divine creation or static species. This groundbreaking mechanism was called natural selection. Darwin and Wallace concluded that all living organisms are shaped by purely natural processes — not by a deity crafting unchanging species once and for all.</p> <p>They identified two fundamental challenges faced by all organisms: survival and reproduction [9,10]. To thrive, individuals must not only survive — by feeding efficiently, avoiding predators and pathogens, and enduring environmental stresses — but also reproduce and produce numerous offspring.</p> <h3 id="the-principle-of-a-scientific-theory"><strong>The Principle of a Scientific Theory</strong></h3> <p>At this point, it’s important to clarify that a scientific theory — like the theory of evolution by natural selection — is not just a guess or a hunch. It’s a well-substantiated explanation of a natural phenomenon, much like the theory of gravity. It has been tested, refined, and supported by extensive empirical evidence.</p> <p>Over time, the theory of evolution has itself evolved — enriched by major scientific discoveries, including the field of genetics.</p> <h2 id="so-how-does-natural-selection-work"><strong>So, How Does Natural Selection Work?</strong></h2> <p>To put it simply: chance proposes, nature disposes!</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG6_NS-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG6_NS-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG6_NS-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG6_NS.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG7_NS-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG7_NS-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG7_NS-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG7_NS.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>We should understand natural selection as a process without intelligence or intention. It has no goal, no purpose in the grand scheme of things. Simply put: chance deals the cards, and nature plays the hand.</p> <p>Imagine, for a moment, a round table where all living species are playing a game of poker. Each species is dealt a hand of cards, shuffled randomly. These cards represent the diversity found both between species and within them.</p> <p>Just like in any card game, the hands are reshuffled with each round. As the game goes on, natural selection favors the most advantageous cards — those traits that provide a benefit in a given environment — ultimately determining the fate of each player at the table.</p> <p>The players (i.e., the species) don’t get to choose which cards to play to stay in the game. Instead, it’s natural selection, as an evolutionary process, that “selects” the players whose hands give them a better shot at surviving and reproducing.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG8_NS-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG8_NS-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG8_NS-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG8_NS.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="but-where-do-these-differences-between-individuals-come-from"><strong>But Where Do These Differences Between Individuals Come From?</strong></h2> <h3 id="one-word-mutations"><strong>One word: mutations!</strong></h3> <p>Mutations can indeed be caused by radioactive elements or ultraviolet radiation from the sun — but those aren’t the only sources in nature. In fact, most mutations arise purely by chance, as a result of tiny errors in the cell’s biological machinery [11].</p> <p>But what kind of errors are we talking about? To understand what a mutation is, we first need to understand what is mutating — and what that means for the species. The answer lies in our genetic blueprint: it’s the DNA that mutates.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG9_NS-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG9_NS-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG9_NS-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG9_NS.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>In genetics, these “letters” are called nucleotides, and together they make up our entire genome. Our genome contains roughly 6.4 billion nucleotides!</p> <p><strong>If each nucleotide were a character in a book, our genome alone would fill about 200 books of 500 pages each!</strong></p> <p>Yet, if we were to unravel all the DNA in our genome and lay it out flat on a table, it would be only about 1.8 millimeters long — incredibly small and incredibly compact.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG10_NS-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG10_NS-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG10_NS-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG10_NS.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Among the 6.4 billion nucleotides that make up your genome, half come from your father and the other half from your mother. In a way, your parents passed down these nucleotides to you at conception.</p> <p>Your DNA is present in every one of your cells — in billions of identical copies. Every second, some cells in your body die while others are created. For new cells to form, your genome must be accurately copied.</p> <p>In other words, it’s like duplicating those 200 books of 500 pages — and doing it countless times!</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG11_NS-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG11_NS-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG11_NS-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG11_NS.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>You’ve just learned how mutations happen — maybe not as spectacular as the X-Men, I admit! Still, while the cellular machinery that copies our DNA sometimes makes mistakes (about 1 error per 100,000 nucleotides), the vast majority of these errors (99%) [12] are repaired, and most of the rest have no real impact. Only occasionally do these errors change the course of a species’ history — and that’s what we’re about to explore!</p> <h2 id="but-what-exactly-is-a-gene"><strong>But What Exactly Is a Gene?</strong></h2> <p>Genes are responsible for the expression of visible traits like eye color, hair color, or the shape of wings, among others. In scientific terms, these traits are called the phenotype.</p> <p>That said, we still need to understand how a mutation in a particular gene can affect an individual. One way to think about genes is like sentences with specific meanings. Change a single letter in the sentence, and its meaning can change completely!</p> <p>Let’s look at an example:</p> <p>“<strong>C</strong>AT ATE RAT” could mutate to: “<strong>B</strong>AT ATE RAT”</p> <p>Here, the animal eating rats changes depending on the version — a small change with a big difference, it is unlikely to see a Bbat eating a rat tho..</p> <p>Now, let’s imagine a hypothetical gene involved in the scale color of a pangolin:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG12_NS-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG12_NS-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG12_NS-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG12_NS.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>During DNA replication, a nucleotide was mistakenly changed from a G to a T. This pangolin now passes down this modified gene to its offspring. It turns out this mutation changes the color of its scales, which become white instead of brown!</p> <p>Now imagine a white pangolin in its natural environment. It would stand out immediately to predators, while a brown pangolin would blend in much more easily. It’s easy to see that, through natural selection, the brown individuals are more likely to survive and reproduce.</p> <h3 id="example-in-humans"><strong>Example in Humans</strong></h3> <p>To convince you even more, why not take a look at our own species? You’ve probably noticed that some of your physical traits resemble those of your mother — and others your father. Yet, you are a unique individual with characteristics that belong only to you!</p> <p>The explanation mainly lies in mutations occurring in the gametes (reproductive cells) of your parents. And, of course, in how you interact with your environment!</p> <p>On average, a child inherits about 175 mutations different from those of their parents [13]. Among these 175 “letters” might be some that give you an advantage in survival or reproduction in the world you live in — who knows?</p> <p>It’s easy to imagine that, after thousands of generations, this process can produce incredible traits:</p> <ul> <li>The telescopic eyes of a hawk ready to swoop on its prey,</li> <li>The incredible strength of a mantis shrimp capable of breaking a skull,</li> <li>Or the majestic aquatic ballet of a blue whale —</li> </ul> <p>These are just a few of the countless amazing examples found across our planet.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG13_NS-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG13_NS-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG13_NS-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG13_NS.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="natural-selection-in-action"><strong>Natural Selection in Action!</strong></h2> <p>To better understand how a mutation can be favored—or not—in a given environment, let’s look at a well-known example: <strong>the peppered moth</strong> [14]!</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG14_NS-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG14_NS-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG14_NS-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG14_NS.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3 id="before-the-industrial-revolution"><strong>Before the Industrial Revolution</strong></h3> <p>In the mid-18th century, the peppered moth (a nocturnal moth) was mostly pale whitish with small black spots. This coloration allowed it to blend in with the light-colored bark of trees such as birches, providing camouflage from potential predators. Dark-colored moths, due to mutations affecting the genes responsible for wing color, stood out against the pale bark and were thus more easily spotted by predators. These mutant individuals had a lower chance of survival and reproduction.</p> <h3 id="during-the-industrial-revolution"><strong>During the Industrial Revolution</strong></h3> <p>As the Industrial Revolution reached its peak, soot pollution in the air increased dramatically. This caused buildings and trees to darken. Consequently, the lighter-colored moths became more visible to predators like birds, making them more vulnerable to predation. This environmental shift reversed the advantage: dark-colored moths now had a higher chance of survival and reproduction. After just a few generations, black-winged moths became the majority in the population.</p> <h2 id="life-is-in-constant-flux"><strong>Life is in Constant Flux</strong></h2> <p>The example of the peppered moth perfectly illustrates the continuous nature of change. However, evolution is neither a simple process marked only by brief periods of rapid change nor a steady, gradual progression. Instead, it is a complex interplay of random (sometimes sudden) changes, a fluctuating environment, and various forms of competition within and between species.</p> <p>These variables ensure that a species is never fixed in time, accumulating variations over generations. Sometimes people talk about “more complex” or “more evolved” species, but these notions have no meaning in evolutionary biology. All living species today have evolved over the same time span within the tree of life.</p> <p>To say that a species is “more or less evolved” would imply that some organisms have stopped evolving altogether. Even so-called “living fossils,” like the coelacanth (a marine animal whose fossil form dates back to the Late Cretaceous), only appear stable externally. Stability in form does not mean absence of change—alterations can happen at molecular or other levels invisible to the eye. Change is intrinsic to all life, at every level, and has been since life began.</p> <h2 id="controversies-around-natural-selection"><strong>Controversies Around Natural Selection</strong></h2> <p>The theory of evolution by natural selection has faced two major controversies:</p> <h3 id="do-humans-descend-from-monkeys"><strong>Do humans descend from monkeys?</strong></h3> <p>As Darwinists, we reject the notion of a hierarchy or “ladder of life.” Yet, doesn’t this idea persist in modern depictions?</p> <p>We’ve all seen the classic image of human evolution: five figures walking in a straight line towards a final goal, <em>Homo sapiens</em> (literally “wise man,” quite the label…).</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG15_NS-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG15_NS-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG15_NS-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG15_NS.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>However, evolution is not directional and does not aim toward any predetermined goal. Humans are therefore not, contrary to what that illustration might suggest, perfect creatures. Every species is constantly evolving. There is no way to measure “progress” in evolution. Thus, the old hierarchical pyramid of life, where humans occupied the pinnacle, has given way to a beautiful egalitarian circle [15], in which every species continues to accumulate variations and evolve!</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG16_NS-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG16_NS-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG16_NS-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG16_NS.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>To sum up, no species is superior to another. If we all share the planet Earth right now—from tiny 3-gram shrimp to majestic African elephants and delicate orchids—it’s because each of us has managed to survive and reproduce.</p> <h2 id="rejections-of-the-theory"><strong>Rejections of the Theory</strong></h2> <p>Today, the theory of evolution is widely accepted, even by many religious institutions. However, it has often been misused, sometimes twisted to justify actions (including political decisions), or outright denied when convenient for those in power. It’s important to be aware of this. Evolutionary theory is a scientific framework that explains how species change over time on our planet. It helps us understand, for example, why a lion might kill all the cubs in a litter that are not his own. What it does not do is tell us whether such behavior is good or bad. Always be cautious when evolution is invoked in political debates or reform proposals. Sociology exists as a distinct discipline from biology—and for very good reasons.</p> <h2 id="final-words"><strong>Final Words</strong></h2> <p>Our body of knowledge is like a glass of water taken from the vast ocean—both insignificant and immense at the same time. Yet, it’s enough to illuminate our minds, or at least mine! You now understand that no species is immutable, not even humans. Each one of us is unique, and it is these differences that natural selection acts upon throughout the evolutionary process.</p> <p>It’s clear that today, the theory of evolution stands on a broad foundation of evidence from diverse scientific fields. Yet there remains much to discover! We are just beginning to unravel the mechanisms of new evolutionary forces that also have major impacts on the trajectories of species. Among these are migration, random genetic drift, and gene transfer between species. We owe these elegant discoveries to passionate researchers who have succeeded each other over time—and who continue, even now, to unravel one of biology’s greatest mysteries: the evolution of species.</p> <p>Author: Benjamin Guinet (Reviewed by: Laura Touzot and Salomé Bourg)</p> <p><a href="https://www.projetpangolin.com/selection-naturelle-mecanismes-exemples-concrets/">French version</a></p> <p><strong>Illustrations:</strong> Salomé Bourg <strong>Reviewing:</strong> The Project Pangolin team</p> <p><strong>References</strong></p> <ol> <li>Hodos W. (2009) Evolution and the Scala Naturae. In: Binder M.D., Hirokawa N., Windhorst U. (eds) Encyclopedia of Neuroscience. Springer, Berlin, Heidelberg. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-540-29678-2_3118</li> <li> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>Gallica.bnf.fr. 2020. Les Sciences Naturelles Au Xviiie Siècle</td> <td>BNF ESSENTIELS.</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> </li> <li>Fitch, W. and Ayala, F., 1995. Tempo And Mode In Evolution. Washington, D.C.: National Academy Press.</li> <li> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>Encyclopedia Britannica. 2020. Jean-Baptiste Lamarck</td> <td>French Biologist.</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> </li> <li>Koonin, E. and Wolf, Y., 2009. Is evolution Darwinian or/and Lamarckian?. Biology Direct, 4(1), p.42.</li> <li>Skinner, M., 2015. Environmental Epigenetics and a Unified Theory of the Molecular Aspects of Evolution: A Neo-Lamarckian Concept that Facilitates Neo-Darwinian Evolution. Genome Biology and Evolution, 7(5), pp.1296-1302.</li> <li>Loison, L., 2018. Lamarckism and epigenetic inheritance: a clarification. Biology &amp; Philosophy, 33(3-4).</li> <li>Ginnobili, S. and Blanco, D., 2017. Wallace’s and Darwin’s natural selection theories. Synthese, 196(3), pp.991-1017.</li> <li>Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882. On The Origin of Species by Means of Natural Selection, or Preservation of Favoured Races in the Struggle for Life. London :John Murray, 1859.</li> <li>Wallace, A., 1870. Contributions To The Theory Of Natural Selection. London: Macmillan.</li> <li>J.F. Griffiths, A., 2020. Mutation. [online] Encyclopedia Britannica.</li> <li>Pray, L.,2008. DNA Replication and Causes of Mutation. Nature Education 1(1):214</li> <li>Asakawa, J., Kodaira, M., Cullings, H., Katayama, H. and Nakamura, N., 2013. The Genetic Risk in Mice from Radiation: An Estimate of the Mutation Induction Rate per Genome. Radiation Research, 179(3), p.293.</li> <li>Cook, L. and Saccheri, I., 2012. The peppered moth and industrial melanism: evolution of a natural selection case study. Heredity, 110(3), pp.207-212.</li> <li>De Vienne, D., 2016. Lifemap: Exploring the Entire Tree of Life. PLOS Biology, 14(12), p.e2001624.</li> </ol> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1"> <p>Lamarck paved the way for a new way of thinking. Perhaps God is not, after all, the driving force behind nature. For those who would come after him, this could be seen as a giant leap forward. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="pop-science"/><category term="Natural"/><category term="selection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Popular scientific paper]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Parasitoid wasps between science fiction, domestication and viruses!</title><link href="https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2025/Pop-science_Parasitoids/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Parasitoid wasps between science fiction, domestication and viruses!"/><published>2025-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2025/Pop-science_Parasitoids</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2025/Pop-science_Parasitoids/"><![CDATA[<p>Translation in progress…</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG1_parasitoids" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG1_parasitoids" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG2_parasitoids" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG2_parasitoids" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG3_parasitoids" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG3_parasitoids" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG4_parasitoids" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG4_parasitoids" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG5_parasitoids" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG5_parasitoids" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG6_parasitoids" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG6_parasitoids" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG7_parasitoids" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG7_parasitoids" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG8_parasitoids" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG8_parasitoids" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG9_parasitoids" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG9_parasitoids" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p><a href="https://www.projetpangolin.com/les-guepes-parasitoides-domestications-virus/">French version</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="pop-science"/><category term="Parasitoids"/><category term="domestications"/><category term="viruses"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Popular scientific paper]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tales lull our childhood and trace our history</title><link href="https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2025/Pop-science-Tales-tel-our-history/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tales lull our childhood and trace our history"/><published>2025-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2025/Pop-science-Tales-tel-our-history</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://benjaminguinet.github.io/blog/2025/Pop-science-Tales-tel-our-history/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Pangolin_pere_castor-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Pangolin_pere_castor-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Pangolin_pere_castor-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Pangolin_pere_castor.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>We’ve all read or heard enchanting tales from fairy tale books—stories that make us dream, tremble, laugh, or reflect. But have you ever wondered where these stories come from? To answer this question, I invite you on a journey through the history of storytelling. Along the way, we’ll see that stories are not only deeply personal, but also woven into the fabric of our shared human history.</p> <p>We’ll begin by exploring the reasons why humans have always created stories—and why we continue to do so. We’ll discover that storytelling is a universal trait: every culture has its tales, which evolve and adapt through the ages.</p> <p>Next, we’ll examine how science—particularly phylogenetics (don’t worry, we’ll explain what that means!)—can be applied to trace the evolution of stories, much like we trace the lineage of living species.</p> <p>Finally, we’ll dive into the rich imaginations of our ancestors by analyzing two stories with particularly intriguing and unusual origins.</p> <ul> <li><a href="#little-red-riding-hood"><strong>Little Red Riding Hood</strong></a></li> <li><a href="#the-cosmic-hunt-in-the-berber-sky"><strong>The Cosmic Hunt in the Berber Sky</strong></a></li> </ul> <p>Now, let’s embark on this fascinating journey together!</p> <h2 id="why-do-humans-tell-stories"><strong>Why do humans tell stories?</strong></h2> <p>Humans have been telling stories for tens of thousands of years—long before writing existed. Like language, stories are a form of information passed down from generation to generation. Through storytelling, we share experiences, convey ideas, and transmit values that help shape how we understand ourselves, our history, and the world around us. But have these stories remained the same over time, or have they evolved with us through the ages?</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG2_tales-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG2_tales-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG2_tales-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG2_tales.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3 id="have-these-stories-evolved-over-the-centuries"><strong>Have these stories evolved over the centuries?</strong></h3> <p>Versions of a story often reflect specific moral standards and mores close to the social classes that tell them. So it’s not unusual to see adaptations that meet the needs of their audience [1].</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG3_tales-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG3_tales-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG3_tales-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG3_tales.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Modern stories, though imprinted in the memories of countless storytellers, have been completely transformed from their original versions. Over time, these stories have been imbued with the various desires, struggles and complaints of their tellers, and provide perfect snapshots of the societies that created or modified them.</p> <p>Let’s take a very famous example. Jean de la Fontaine wrote a fable called ‘The Court of the Lion’, which is a story inspired by another fable called ‘The Reigning King’ written by Phaedra. Jean de la Fontaine modified the story to make it rhyme and, above all, to reflect the reality of Louis XIV’s court.</p> <h3 id="is-storytelling-universal"><strong>Is storytelling universal?</strong></h3> <p>Across centuries and continents, stories have always been tied to specific times and cultures [2]. Think of biblical tales like Noah’s Ark, Greek myths such as Narcissus, or even more recent legends like Slenderman, which emerged on the internet in the early 2000s. Many stories are closely associated with particular cultural origins—for example, Peter and the Wolf in Russian folklore, Hansel and Gretel in German tradition, Le Petit Poucet (Little Thumb) in French tales, and Ali Baba and the Forty Thieves from Persian and Arabic lore.</p> <p>What’s particularly intriguing is that when you leaf through the pages of the famous Grimm brothers’ collection [3], you start to notice striking similarities between some of these tales. Take Little Red Riding Hood, for instance—a story that appears in surprisingly similar forms across many different cultures. (Stay with us—we’ll dive deeper into this fascinating example a bit later!)</p> <h2 id="using-biology-to-solve-folklore-problems"><strong>Using biology to solve folklore problems</strong></h2> <p><strong>A question then arises in folkloristics (the study of popular traditions and customs): where do these stories come from?</strong></p> <p>To explore the origins and evolution of stories, we must rely on the traces that have withstood the passage of time. Yet most of these tales have been passed down orally, leaving behind few written records—much like the sparse fossil evidence available to paleontologists. This makes tracing the history of stories particularly challenging, even with the tools of traditional literary analysis.</p> <p>To overcome these limitations, a promising new approach in folkloristics has emerged: the application of mathematical methods borrowed from biology to study the evolution of storytelling [4–6]. Just as biologists reconstruct the evolutionary trees of living species, researchers can now use similar tools to map the branching paths of narrative traditions across cultures and time.</p> <h3 id="but-how-does-it-work"><strong>But how does it work?</strong></h3> <p>To better understand how these mathematical tools work, let’s first draw a parallel with the evolution of species and how scientists reconstruct their history.</p> <p>The theory of evolution—which explains the incredible diversity of life on Earth—was developed in the mid-19th century by biologists such as Charles Darwin and Alfred Russel Wallace [7]. In simple terms (see our article on the topic for more details), evolution describes how organisms change over time through genetic variation. These changes can affect an organism’s physical traits or behavior. If a particular change proves beneficial, it is more likely to be passed down to future generations. This foundational theory—and the scientific advances that followed—transformed how we understand the living world.</p> <p>One powerful tool that emerged from this theory is phylogeny: the study of the evolutionary relationships among organisms.</p> <p>Wait—“phylogeny”? That might sound like an intimidating word, but it’s not so scary once you break it down. It comes from the Greek phylon, meaning “tribe” or “species”, and gennan, meaning “to produce” or “to generate”. So, phylogeny quite literally means <strong>the study of the formation of species</strong>. In practice, it helps scientists trace how living organisms have evolved over time and how they are related to one another.</p> <h3 id="the-link-between-phylogeny-and-fairytales"><strong>The link between phylogeny and fairytales</strong></h3> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG4_tales-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG4_tales-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG4_tales-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG4_tales.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>ou might be wondering—what does phylogeny have to do with stories? As the renowned anthropologist Claude Lévi-Strauss once observed [8], stories, much like living organisms, likely evolve through the gradual accumulation of inherited traits. Just as species change over time, the earliest versions of stories adapt, mutate, and diversify as they are passed from one generation to the next. As they spread across cultures and environments, these tales evolve—sometimes subtly, sometimes dramatically—giving rise to distinct local variations.</p> <p>To study how stories differ across cultures and historical periods, researchers identify a set of defining features, or “mythemes,” which they can compare across story variants.</p> <p>These features might include the gender of the protagonist (girl or boy), the nature of the antagonist (wolf, tiger, ogre), or the setting of the tale (forest, village, mountain). By analyzing these elements, we can trace how stories transform and branch out—just like species on an evolutionary tree.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG5_tales-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG5_tales-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG5_tales-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG5_tales.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>The idea is to analyse these characteristics as if they were physical characteristics or genes and to use them to reconstruct the genealogy of the story, just as we would for a species phylogeny. So, if two histories have similar characteristics, it is likely that they have a recent common origin.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG6_tales-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG6_tales-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG6_tales-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG6_tales.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="little-red-riding-hood"><strong>Little Red Riding Hood</strong></h2> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG9_tales-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG9_tales-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG9_tales-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG9_tales.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Little Red Riding Hood is one of the world’s most popular tales. This tale delicately explores our greatest fears. It’s a story about the struggle between good and evil, about greed and hope, about responsibility and second chances.</p> <h3 id="the-classic-tale"><strong>The classic tale</strong></h3> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG7_tales-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG7_tales-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG7_tales-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG7_tales.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>If this story sounds familiar, it’s because you’ve likely inherited the French version of Little Red Riding Hood, first written by Charles Perrault in the late 17th century [9,10] and later popularized by the Grimm brothers in their famous collection [3].</p> <p>But if you’re raising an eyebrow and thinking, “Wait, that’s not how I remember it,” you’re not alone—and you’re absolutely right. There are many different versions of this tale from around the world! In some, there’s no heroic hunter at all, and the girl cleverly escapes by pretending she needs to go outside for a call of nature. In others, the iconic red hood is completely absent. Each version carries its own twist, shaped by the culture and time in which it was told.</p> <h3 id="strangely-similar-tales"><strong>Strangely similar tales</strong></h3> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG8_tales-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG8_tales-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG8_tales-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG8_tales.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Striking similarities to Little Red Riding Hood, don’t you think?</p> <p>What’s even more intriguing is that tales with nearly identical structures and themes can be found in many parts of the world—including across Africa and East Asia [10–11]. This raises a fascinating question: could all these stories share a common origin?</p> <p>Now, what if I told you that to explore this question, we can actually turn to the biological methods we discussed earlier? Surprising, isn’t it?</p> <h3 id="little-red-riding-hood-an-old-story"><strong>Little Red Riding Hood: an old story</strong></h3> <p>Even before scientific studies entered the picture, anthropologists were captivated by the parallels between <em>Little Red Riding Hood</em> and <em>The Wolf and the Seven Young Goats</em>. The similarities were so pronounced that researchers long debated whether these stories stemmed from a shared ancestral tale or had developed independently. The question remained open—until new methods offered a fresh perspective.</p> <p>To unravel these questions, one researcher conducted a phylogenetic study of the <em>Little Red Riding Hood</em> story. He examined 58 versions of the tale and identified no fewer than 72 distinct plot variants [12]! And to trace their origins, there was only one option: read them all. As you can imagine, collecting such a vast dataset is no small task. It often involves making choices—some more debatable than others [13]. Still, this pioneering study opened the door for future folklorists to take a more rigorous and systematic approach.</p> <h3 id="geographical-origins"><strong>Geographical Origins</strong></h3> <p>The results revealed that both Little Red Riding Hood and The Wolf and the Seven Young Goats originated in Europe. Traces of Little Red Riding Hood can be found as early as the Middle Ages [14]. However, the two stories differ enough in structure and content to be considered separate tales with distinct origins.</p> <p>Variants found in Africa appear to be adapted versions of The Wolf and the Seven Young Goats. Researchers believe this tale was introduced through trade or colonial contact, later evolving into a localized version that spread throughout central and southern Africa—even reaching the Caribbean islands.</p> <p>In contrast, the Asian tale The Tiger and the Grandmother seems to be a fascinating hybrid, blending elements from both Little Red Riding Hood and The Wolf and the Seven Young Goats. Yet its exact origins remain something of a mystery.</p> <p>Fascinating, isn’t it?</p> <p>And if you’re still not convinced of the power of phylogenetic tools to study the evolution of fairy tales, don’t worry—we have one more captivating example coming up.</p> <h2 id="the-cosmic-hunt-in-the-berber-sky"><strong>The Cosmic hunt in the Berber sky</strong></h2> <h3 id="15000-years-ago"><strong>15,000 years ago…</strong></h3> <p>Let’s continue with a much older story.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG10_tales-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG10_tales-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG10_tales-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG10_tales.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>In the Palaeolithic era, when our ancestors still lived as hunter-gatherers, the world as we know it today didn’t exist. The cap wasn’t invented until the early 19th century, the crown dates back to Antiquity, and even the object we now call a saucepan is a relatively recent innovation. Humans of that time had a completely different relationship with their environment—one that was far more attuned to nature. But how can we possibly glimpse what they imagined?</p> <p>What if I told you that, once again, phylogenetic methods offer a way to infer the contents of our ancestors’ imaginations? You’d be right to be sceptical—but the approach is genuinely intriguing and deserves a closer look.</p> <h3 id="the-myth"><strong>The Myth</strong></h3> <p>It all begins with a tale found across continents—in Africa, Europe, Asia, and the Americas [15]: the Cosmic Hunt. While the characters and constellations vary, all versions share a central narrative thread: a man pursues or kills one or more animals, and these animals are ultimately transformed into stars.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG11_tales-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG11_tales-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG11_tales-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG11_tales.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Versions of the Cosmic Hunt can be found all over the world. Take, for example, the tale of the Iroquois peoples of North America. In their story, three hunters chase a bear whose blood stains the autumn leaves as it flees. The bear climbs a mountain and leaps into the sky, transforming along with the hunters into the constellation of the Big Dipper. Meanwhile, among the Chukchi of Siberia, the constellation Orion represents a hunter pursuing a reindeer, while Cassiopeia plays a key role in their celestial stories.</p> <p>How can we explain these striking similarities across such distant cultures? One possible explanation is the convergence hypothesis—that these myths arose independently in separate regions due to similar human experiences or a shared collective subconscious. In other words, different peoples might have crafted similar stories because certain symbols and themes resonate universally when trying to make sense of the world.</p> <p>However, this theory isn’t the most convincing one, especially in light of the research conducted by a researcher who offers a different perspective.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FIG12_tales-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FIG12_tales-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FIG12_tales-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/FIG12_tales.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="the-phylogenetic-study"><strong>The phylogenetic study</strong></h2> <p>In this study, the researcher analyzed 47 versions of the story and identified 93 distinct variants [15]. Interestingly, these versions are rarely found in Australia and virtually absent from Indonesia and New Guinea. In contrast, many versions appear on both sides of the Bering Strait—the stretch of water that once connected Eastern Siberia and Alaska about 20,000 years ago, when it was above sea level [16,17]. Taken together with phylogenetic reconstructions, these findings suggest that the story has a very ancient origin, tracing back to the common ancestors of Berber populations and European hunter-gatherers.</p> <p>Data on human migrations further support this hypothesis. As our ancestors migrated from Eurasia into the Americas—crossing the Bering land bridge before it was submerged under rising seas—they likely carried this story with them. The presence of the tale in Africa also aligns with the well-established theory that humans later migrated back from Eurasia into the African continent.</p> <p>The researcher even attempted to reconstruct the original version of the myth, imagining what our ancestors might have envisioned more than 15,000 years ago. Here is the proposed narrative: “A large herbivore, probably an elk, is chased by a hunter. To escape, the elk gallops up into the sky, where it transforms in a burst of light into a cluster of stars—the constellation we now call the Big Dipper.”</p> <p>Of course, this reconstruction is only an approximation. Still, it offers a fascinating glimpse into the imagination of our distant ancestors and invites us to envision how these ancient stories might have taken shape.</p> <p>This is just one example, but many others can be found in the literature—for instance, the tale of <em>The Smith and the Devil</em>, which was adapted into a Netflix film in the Basque language, can be traced back to the Bronze Age [18].</p> <h2 id="conclusion-between-tales-and-stories"><strong>Conclusion, between tales and stories</strong></h2> <p>It is truly remarkable that these stories have survived for millennia without ever being written down. They were passed along long before our modern languages existed, spoken in dialects now lost to time. Yet, through the enduring power of storytelling, these tales have persevered. Their motifs are timeless and universal—exploring fundamental dichotomies such as good versus evil, love versus hate, and moral versus immoral. Though often dismissed as mere fiction or children’s narratives, folk tales continue to nourish and enrich our collective imagination.</p> <h2 id="final-word"><strong>Final word</strong></h2> <p>Over the centuries, the ways we tell stories have evolved dramatically. In humanity’s earliest days, our ancestors likely gathered around a fire, weaving tales born from their natural surroundings and vivid imaginations. Today, stories are shared instantly with a click. We are privileged to have access to this vast legacy of storytelling—and we should cherish it. But more importantly, we must keep sharing these stories and let them inspire us to create new ones. Because if there is one thing humanity can truly be proud of, it is the boundless power of our imagination.</p> <p><strong>Illustrations:</strong> Vincent Lhuillier <strong>Reviewing:</strong> The Project Pangolin team</p> <p><a href="https://www.projetpangolin.com/les-contes-bercent-notre-enfance-et-retracent-notre-histoire/">French version</a></p> <h2 id="references"><strong>References</strong></h2> <ol> <li> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>Encyclopedia.com., 2020. Evolution Of Fairy Tales</td> <td>Encyclopedia.Com.</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> </li> <li>Hughes, H., 1998. Storytelling Encyclopedia:98252David Adams Leeming, Marion Sader Edited by. Storytelling Encyclopedia: Historical, Cultural, and Multiethnic Approaches to Oral Traditions Around the World. Phoenix, Az. and London</li> <li>Grimm J, Grimm W., 1812. Children’s and Household Tales. Gottingen.</li> <li>Julien d’Huy et Jean-Loïc Le Quellec., 2004. « Comment reconstruire la préhistoire des mythes ? Applications d’outils phylogénétiques à une tradition orale »</li> <li>Korotayev, D, Khaltourina., 2011. Myths and Genes: a Deep Historical Reconstruction. Moscow: Librokom/URSS (ISBN 978–5–397–01175–4)</li> <li>Thuillard, M., Le Quellec, J., d’Huy, J. and Berezkin, Y., 2018. A Large-Scale Dtudy of World. Trames. Journal of the Humanities and Social Sciences, 22(4), p.407.</li> <li>Darwin, C. R. &amp; A. R. Wallace., 1858. Proceedings of the meeting of the Linnean Society held on July 1st, 1858. Journal of the Proceedings of the Linnean Society. Zoology 3: liv-lvi.</li> <li>Lévi-Strauss Claude., 1971. Mythologique4. L’Homme nu. Paris, Plon, 681p.</li> <li>Perrault C.,1697. Histoires ou Contes du temps passe´. Hood’’. Speculum 67: 549–575</li> <li>Frazer JG., 1889. A South African Red Riding-Hood. The Folk-Lore Journal 7:</li> <li>Ikeda H., 1971. A Type and Motif Index of Japanese Folk Literature. Helsinki: FF Communications</li> <li>Jamshid J. Tehrani., 2013. The Phylogeny of Little Red Riding Hood, PLOS ONE, vol. 8, n°11: e78871.</li> <li>Patrice Lajoye, Julien d’Huy and Jean-Loïc Le Quellec., 2013. reply to tethrani ; http://nouvellemythologiecomparee.hautetfort.com</li> <li>Ziolkowski JM., 1992. A fairy tale from before fairy tales: Egbert of Liege’s ‘‘De puella a lupellis seruata’’ and the medieval background of ‘‘Little Red Riding</li> <li>Julien d’Huy. A Cosmic Hunt in the Berber sky: : a phylogenetic reconstruction of a Palaeolithic mythology.. Les Cahiers de l’AARS, 2013, 15, pp.93-106. ￿halshs-00932197￿</li> <li>Bond, J.D., 2019. Paleodrainage map of Beringia. Yukon Geological Survey,</li> <li>Geggel, L., 2019. Humans Crossed The Bering Land Bridge To People The Americas. Here’S What It Looked Like 18,000 Years Ago.. [online] livescience.com.</li> <li>Da Silva, S. and Tehrani, J., 2016. Comparative phylogenetic analyses uncover the ancient roots of Indo-European folktales. Royal Society Open Science, 3(1), p.150645.</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="pop-science"/><category term="Tales"/><category term="trace"/><category term="our"/><category term="history"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Popular scientific paper]]></summary></entry></feed>